<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><xml><records><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521697</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tang, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Platek, ME.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yao, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Till, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Goodman, PJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tangen, CM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wu, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Platz, EA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Neuhouser, ML.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Stanczyk, FZ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Reichardt, JKV.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Santella, RM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hsing, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Figg, WD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lippman, SM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thompson, IM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ambrosone, CB.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Associations between polymorphisms in genes related to estrogen metabolism and function and prostate cancer risk: results from the Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carcinogenesis</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carcinogenesis</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Substantial preclinical data suggest estrogen's carcinogenic role in prostate cancer development; however, epidemiological evidence based on circulating estrogen levels is largely null. Compared with circulating estrogen, the intraprostatic estrogen milieu may play a more important role in prostate carcinogenesis. Using a nested case-control design in the Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial (PCPT), we examined associations of genetic variants of genes that are involved in estrogen synthesis, metabolism and function with prostate cancer risk. A total of 25 potentially functional single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in 13 genes (PGR, ESR1, ESR2, CYP17A1, HSD17B1, CYP19A1, CYP1A1, CYP1B1, COMT, UGT1A6, UGT1A10, UGT2B7, UGT2B15) were examined in whites only. Controls (n = 1380) were frequency matched to cases on age, PCPT treatment arm, and family history (n = 1506). Logistic regression models adjusted for age and family history were used to estimate odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) separately in the placebo and finasteride arms. SNPs associated with prostate cancer risk differed by treatment arm. The associations appeared to be modified by circulating estrogen and androgen levels. CYP19A1 was the only gene harboring SNPs that were significantly associated with risk in both the placebo and finasteride arms. Haplotype analysis with all three CYP19A1 SNPs genotyped (rs700518, rs2445765, rs700519) showed that risk-allele haplotypes are associated with the increased prostate cancer risk in both arms when comparing with the non-risk allele haplotype. In conclusion, associations between SNPs in estrogen-related genes and prostate cancer risk are complex and may be modified by circulating hormone levels and finasteride treatment.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521697</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521696</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Aggarwal, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Huang, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Alumkal, JJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zhang, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Feng, FY.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thomas, GV.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Weinstein, AS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Friedl, V.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zhang, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Witte, ON.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lloyd, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gleave, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Evans, CP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Youngren, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Beer, TM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rettig, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wong, CK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">True, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Foye, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Playdle, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ryan, CJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lara, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chi, KN.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Uzunangelov, V.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sokolov, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Newton, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Beltran, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Demichelis, F.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rubin, MA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Stuart, JM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Small, EJ.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical and Genomic Characterization of Treatment-Emergent Small-Cell Neuroendocrine Prostate Cancer: A Multi-institutional Prospective Study.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Purpose The prevalence and features of treatment-emergent small-cell neuroendocrine prostate cancer (t-SCNC) are not well characterized in the era of modern androgen receptor (AR)-targeting therapy. We sought to characterize the clinical and genomic features of t-SCNC in a multi-institutional prospective study. Methods Patients with progressive, metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer (mCRPC) underwent metastatic tumor biopsy and were followed for survival. Metastatic biopsy specimens underwent independent, blinded pathology review along with RNA/DNA sequencing. Results A total of 202 consecutive patients were enrolled. One hundred forty-eight (73%) had prior disease progression on abiraterone and/or enzalutamide. The biopsy evaluable rate was 79%. The overall incidence of t-SCNC detection was 17%. AR amplification and protein expression were present in 67% and 75%, respectively, of t-SCNC biopsy specimens. t-SCNC was detected at similar proportions in bone, node, and visceral organ biopsy specimens. Genomic alterations in the DNA repair pathway were nearly mutually exclusive with t-SCNC differentiation ( P = .035). Detection of t-SCNC was associated with shortened overall survival among patients with prior AR-targeting therapy for mCRPC (hazard ratio, 2.02; 95% CI, 1.07 to 3.82). Unsupervised hierarchical clustering of the transcriptome identified a small-cell-like cluster that further enriched for adverse survival outcomes (hazard ratio, 3.00; 95% CI, 1.25 to 7.19). A t-SCNC transcriptional signature was developed and validated in multiple external data sets with &gt; 90% accuracy. Multiple transcriptional regulators of t-SCNC were identified, including the pancreatic neuroendocrine marker PDX1. Conclusion t-SCNC is present in nearly one fifth of patients with mCRPC and is associated with shortened survival. The near-mutual exclusivity with DNA repair alterations suggests t-SCNC may be a distinct subset of mCRPC. Transcriptional profiling facilitates the identification of t-SCNC and novel therapeutic targets.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521696</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521695</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Deeken, JF.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cormier, T.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Price, DK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sissung, TM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Steinberg, SM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tran, K.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Liewehr, DJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dahut, WL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Miao, X.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Figg, WD.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A pharmacogenetic study of docetaxel and thalidomide in patients with castration-resistant prostate cancer using the DMET genotyping platform.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The pharmacogenomics journal</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The pharmacogenomics journal</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2010</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The anticancer agent docetaxel shows significant inter-individual variation in its pharmacokinetic and toxicity profile. Thalidomide is an active anticancer agent and also shows wide pharmacological variation. Past pharmacogenetic research has not explained this variation. Patients with prostate cancer enrolled in a randomized phase II trial using docetaxel and thalidomide versus docetaxel alone were genotyped using the Affymetrix DMET 1.0 platform, which tests for 1256 genetic variations in 170 drug disposition genes. Genetic polymorphisms were analyzed for associations with clinical response and toxicity. In all, 10 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in three genes were potentially associated with response to therapy: peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-delta (PPAR-delta), sulfotransferase family, cytosolic, 1C, member 2 (SULT1C2) and carbohydrate (chondroitin 6) sulfotransferase 3 (CHST3). In addition, 11 SNPs in eight genes were associated with toxicities to treatment: spastic paraplegia 7 (pure and complicated autosomal recessive) (SPG7), CHST3, cytochrome P450, family 2, subfamily D, polypeptide 6 (CYP2D6), N-acetyltransferase 2 (arylamine N-acetyltransferase) (NAT2), ATP-binding cassette, sub-family C (CFTR/MRP), member 6 (ABCC6), ATPase, Cu++ transporting, alpha polypeptide (ATP7A), cytochrome P450, family 4, subfamily B, polypeptide 1 (CYP4B1) and solute carrier family 10 (sodium/bile acid cotransporter family), member 2 (SLC10A2). Genotyping results between drug metabolizing enzymes and transporters (DMET) and direct sequencing showed &gt;96% of concordance. These findings highlight the role that non-CYP450 metabolizing enzymes and transporters may have in the pharmacology of docetaxel and thalidomide.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521695</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521694</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yu, HA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Schoenfeld, AJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Makhnin, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kim, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rizvi, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tsui, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Falcon, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Houck-Loomis, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Meng, F.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yang, JL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tobi, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Heller, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ahn, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hayes, SA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Young, RJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Arcila, ME.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Berger, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chaft, JE.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ladanyi, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Riely, GJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kris, MG.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Effect of Osimertinib and Bevacizumab on Progression-Free Survival for Patients With Metastatic EGFR-Mutant Lung Cancers: A Phase 1/2 Single-Group Open-Label Trial.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">JAMA oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">JAMA oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2021</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Importance: The combination of erlotinib and bevacizumab as initial treatment of epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR [OMIM 131550])-mutant lung cancers improves progression-free survival (PFS) compared with erlotinib alone. Because osimertinib prolongs PFS compared with erlotinib, this trial was designed to study the combination of osimertinib and bevacizumab as first-line treatment.

Objectives: To determine the safety and tolerability of osimertinib and bevacizumab combination treatment and assess the 12-month PFS of the combination in patients with metastatic EGFR-mutant lung cancers.

Design, Setting, and Particiants: From August 15, 2016, to May 15, 2018, 49 patients with metastatic EGFR-mutant lung cancers were enrolled in this interventional clinical trial, conducted at a single academic cancer center. In the phase 1 portion of the study, a standard 3 + 3 dose de-escalation design was used to determine the maximum tolerated dose of osimertinib and bevacizumab. In the phase 2 portion of the study, patients were treated at the maximum tolerated dose defined in the phase 1 portion. Statistical analysis was performed from August 1 to October 1, 2019.

Interventions: All patients received osimertinib, 80 mg daily, and bevacizumab, 15 mg/kg once every 3 weeks.

Main Outcomes and Measures: The primary objective of the phase 2 portion of the study was to determine the number of patients receiving the combination of osimertinib and bevacizumab who were progression free at 12 months. Secondary end points included overall response rate, median PFS, overall survival, and definition of the toxic effects of the combination treatment.

Results: Among the 49 patients in the study (34 women; median age, 60 years [range, 36-83 years]), PFS at 12 months was 76% (95% CI, 65%-90%). The overall response rate was 80% (95% CI, 67%-91%), and median PFS was 19 months (95% CI, 15-24 months). Of the 6 patients with measurable central nervous system disease, all had a partial or complete central nervous system response. Persistent detection of EGFR-mutant circulating tumor (ct)DNA at 6 weeks was associated with shorter median PFS (clearance at 6 weeks, 16.2 months [95% CI, 13 months to not reached]; and no clearance at 6 weeks, 9.8 months [95% CI, 4 months to not reached]; P = .04) and median overall survival (clearance at 6 weeks, not reached; and no clearance at 6 weeks, 10.1 months [95% CI, 6 months to not reached]; P = .002). Identified mechanisms of resistance included squamous cell transformation (n = 2) pleomorphic transformation (n = 1), and acquired EGFR L718Q (n = 1) and C797S (n = 1) mutations.

Conclusions and Relevance: The combination of osimertinib and bevacizumab met the study's prespecified effectiveness end point. Persistent EGFR-mutant circulating tumor DNA at 6 weeks was associated with early progression and shorter survival. A randomized phase 3 study comparing osimertinib and bevacizumab with osimertinib alone is planned.

Trial Registration: ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT02803203.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521694</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521693</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Goodall, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mateo, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yuan, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mossop, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Porta, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Miranda, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Perez-Lopez, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dolling, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Robinson, DR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sandhu, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Fowler, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ebbs, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Flohr, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Seed, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rodrigues, DN.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Boysen, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bertan, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Atkin, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clarke, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Crespo, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Figueiredo, I.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Riisnaes, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sumanasuriya, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rescigno, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zafeiriou, Z.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sharp, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tunariu, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bianchini, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gillman, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lord, CJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hall, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chinnaiyan, AM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carreira, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">de Bono, JS.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Circulating Cell-Free DNA to Guide Prostate Cancer Treatment with PARP Inhibition.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer discovery</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer discovery</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2017</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Biomarkers for more precise patient care are needed in metastatic prostate cancer. We have reported a phase II trial (TOPARP-A) of the PARP inhibitor olaparib in metastatic prostate cancer, demonstrating antitumor activity associating with homologous recombination DNA repair defects. We now report targeted and whole-exome sequencing of serial circulating cell-free DNA (cfDNA) samples collected during this trial. Decreases in cfDNA concentration independently associated with outcome in multivariable analyses (HR for overall survival at week 8: 0.19; 95% CI, 0.06-0.56;&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;= 0.003). All tumor tissue somatic DNA repair mutations were detectable in cfDNA; allele frequency of somatic mutations decreased selectively in responding patients (χ&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;&lt; 0.001). At disease progression, following response to olaparib, multiple subclonal aberrations reverting germline and somatic DNA repair mutations (&lt;i&gt;BRCA2, PALB2&lt;/i&gt;) back in frame emerged as mechanisms of resistance. These data support the role of liquid biopsies as a predictive, prognostic, response, and resistance biomarker in metastatic prostate cancer.&lt;b&gt;Significance:&lt;/b&gt;We report prospectively planned, serial, cfDNA analyses from patients with metastatic prostate cancer treated on an investigator-initiated phase II trial of olaparib. These analyses provide predictive, prognostic, response, and resistance data with "second hit" mutations first detectable at disease progression, suggesting clonal evolution from treatment-selective pressure and platinum resistance.&lt;i&gt;Cancer Discov; 7(9); 1006-17. ©2017 AACR.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;See related commentary by Domchek, p. 937&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;See related article by Kondrashova et al., p. 984&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;See related article by Quigley et al., p. 999&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;This article is highlighted in the In This Issue feature, p. 920&lt;/i&gt;.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521693</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521692</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Efstathiou, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Davis, JW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pisters, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Li, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wen, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">McMullin, RP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gormley, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ricci, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Titus, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hoang, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zurita, AJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tran, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Peng, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kheoh, T.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Molina, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Troncoso, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Logothetis, CJ.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical and Biological Characterisation of Localised High-risk Prostate Cancer: Results of a Randomised Preoperative Study of a Luteinising Hormone-releasing Hormone Agonist with or Without Abiraterone Acetate plus Prednisone.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">European urology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">European urology</style></full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Abiraterone acetate</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Androgen deprivation therapy</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Androgen receptor</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Androgen receptor splice variant</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Glucocorticoid receptor</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">High-risk localised prostate cancer</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Neoadjuvant</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Preoperative</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Radical prostatectomy</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tumour volume</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2021</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Optimal therapeutic strategy remains an unmet need in localised high-risk prostate cancer (LHRPC). Androgen biosynthesis inhibition in the preoperative setting may improve outcomes. In this single-centre randomised trial, we looked at therapy outcomes of preoperative treatment with abiraterone acetate+prednisone (AAP)+luteinising hormone-releasing hormone agonist (LHRHa) or LHRHa alone followed by radical prostatectomy in 65 men. We did not see a significant difference of organ-confined carcinoma (p=0.27). However, tumour volume measures were significantly lower for AAP+LHRHa treatment (p≤0.001). Of note, lower tumour epithelium volume correlated with improved biochemical recurrence-free survival at ≥4-yr follow-up (p=0.0014). Tumours pretreated with AAP+LHRHa had lower proliferation and androgen signalling expression than LHRHa. On multivariate analysis, glucocorticoid receptor (GR) overexpression correlated with persistent tumours in AAP+LHRHa (p=0.018). The presence of nuclear androgen receptor splice variant (nARV7) correlated with persistent tumours in both arms. No new safety signals were observed. This is the first study investigating the role of preoperative AAP+LHRHa versus LHRHa alone in LHRPC. We report significant cytoreduction by tumour volume measures inversely correlating with biochemical relapse. Validation of these proposed tumour volume measures is planned. A potential role of GR in resistance to androgen biosynthesis inhibition warrants further study. PATIENT SUMMARY: This is the first study of abiraterone acetate plus leuprolide versus leuprolide alone in high-risk localised prostate cancer followed by prostatectomy. Patients in the combination arm had a significantly smaller tumour size.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521692</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521691</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kerns, SL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Stock, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Stone, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Buckstein, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Shao, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Campbell, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rath, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">De Ruysscher, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lammering, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hixson, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cesaretti, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Terk, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ostrer, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rosenstein, BS.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A 2-stage genome-wide association study to identify single nucleotide polymorphisms associated with development of erectile dysfunction following radiation therapy for prostate cancer.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">International journal of radiation oncology, biology, physics</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">International journal of radiation oncology, biology, physics</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2013</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PURPOSE: To identify single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) associated with development of erectile dysfunction (ED) among prostate cancer patients treated with radiation therapy.

METHODS AND MATERIALS: A 2-stage genome-wide association study was performed. Patients were split randomly into a stage I discovery cohort (132 cases, 103 controls) and a stage II replication cohort (128 cases, 102 controls). The discovery cohort was genotyped using Affymetrix 6.0 genome-wide arrays. The 940 top ranking SNPs selected from the discovery cohort were genotyped in the replication cohort using Illumina iSelect custom SNP arrays.

RESULTS: Twelve SNPs identified in the discovery cohort and validated in the replication cohort were associated with development of ED following radiation therapy (Fisher combined P values 2.1×10(-5) to 6.2×10(-4)). Notably, these 12 SNPs lie in or near genes involved in erectile function or other normal cellular functions (adhesion and signaling) rather than DNA damage repair. In a multivariable model including nongenetic risk factors, the odds ratios for these SNPs ranged from 1.6 to 5.6 in the pooled cohort. There was a striking relationship between the cumulative number of SNP risk alleles an individual possessed and ED status (Sommers' D P value=1.7×10(-29)). A 1-allele increase in cumulative SNP score increased the odds for developing ED by a factor of 2.2 (P value=2.1×10(-19)). The cumulative SNP score model had a sensitivity of 84% and specificity of 75% for prediction of developing ED at the radiation therapy planning stage.

CONCLUSIONS: This genome-wide association study identified a set of SNPs that are associated with development of ED following radiation therapy. These candidate genetic predictors warrant more definitive validation in an independent cohort.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521691</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521690</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Barnett, GC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Coles, CE.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Elliott, RM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Baynes, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Luccarini, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Conroy, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wilkinson, JS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tyrer, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Misra, V.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Platte, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gulliford, SL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sydes, MR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hall, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bentzen, SM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dearnaley, DP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Burnet, NG.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pharoah, PD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dunning, AM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">West, CM.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Independent validation of genes and polymorphisms reported to be associated with radiation toxicity: a prospective analysis study.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The Lancet. Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The Lancet. Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2012</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: Several studies have reported associations between radiation toxicity and single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in candidate genes. Few associations have been tested in independent validation studies. This prospective study aimed to validate reported associations between genotype and radiation toxicity in a large independent dataset.

METHODS: 92 (of 98 attempted) SNPs in 46 genes were successfully genotyped in 1613 patients: 976 received adjuvant breast radiotherapy in the Cambridge breast IMRT trial (ISRCTN21474421, n=942) or in a prospective study of breast toxicity at the Christie Hospital, Manchester, UK (n=34). A further 637 received radical prostate radiotherapy in the MRC RT01 multicentre trial (ISRCTN47772397, n=224) or in the Conventional or Hypofractionated High Dose Intensity Modulated Radiotherapy for Prostate Cancer (CHHiP) trial (ISRCTN97182923, n=413). Late toxicity was assessed 2 years after radiotherapy with a validated photographic technique (patients with breast cancer only), clinical assessment, and patient questionnaires. Association tests of genotype with overall radiation toxicity score and individual endpoints were undertaken in univariate and multivariable analyses. At a type I error rate adjusted for multiple testing, this study had 99% power to detect a SNP, with minor allele frequency of 0·35, associated with a per allele odds ratio of 2·2.

FINDINGS: None of the previously reported associations were confirmed by this study, after adjustment for multiple comparisons. The p value distribution of the SNPs tested against overall toxicity score was not different from that expected by chance.

INTERPRETATION: We did not replicate previously reported late toxicity associations, suggesting that we can essentially exclude the hypothesis that published SNPs individually exert a clinically relevant effect. Continued recruitment of patients into studies within the Radiogenomics Consortium is essential so that sufficiently powered studies can be done and methodological challenges addressed.

FUNDING: Cancer Research UK, The Royal College of Radiologists, Addenbrooke's Charitable Trust, Breast Cancer Campaign, Cambridge National Institute of Health Research (NIHR) Biomedical Research Centre, Experimental Cancer Medicine Centre, East Midlands Innovation, the National Cancer Institute, Joseph Mitchell Trust, Royal Marsden NHS Foundation Trust, Institute of Cancer Research NIHR Biomedical Research Centre for Cancer.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521690</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521689</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ando, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Price, DK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dahut, WL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cox, MC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Reed, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Figg, WD.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pharmacogenetic associations of CYP2C19 genotype with in vivo metabolisms and pharmacological effects of thalidomide.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer biology &amp; therapy</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer biology &amp; therapy</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2003</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thalidomide requires cytochrome P450 (CYP)-catalyzed biotransformation for its antiangiogenic property, and CYP2C19 is responsible for 5-hydroxylation and 5'-hydroxylation of thalidomide in human. This study explored a hypothesis that patients with poor metabolizing phenotype of CYP2C19 receive little benefit from thalidomide treatment and that the poor metabolizer genotype is associated with lower ability to form the metabolites. A case-control study was conducted with 63 patients with prostate cancer who had been enrolled in a randomized phase II trial of thalidomide monotherapy (200 to 1,200 mg/day). CYP2C19 polymorphism (CYP2C19(*)2, CYP2C19(*)3, CYP2C19(*)4) was compared with clinical events (prostate-specific antigen (PSA) decline) and formations of the hydroxylated metabolites. Two patients were homozygous for the variant CYP2C19(*)2 allele (poor metabolizing phenotype). Both of these were included in the 25 patients whose PSA failed to demonstrate a decline. While 32% and 48% of the patients had quantifiable levels of 5-hydroxythalidomide and cis-5'-hydroxythalidomide, respectively, these metabolite were below quantification in both poor metabolizing patients. None had CYP2C19(*)3 or CYP2C19(*)4 alleles. Although this study had no power to detect the statistical significance of the CYP2C19 genotype, the findings were consistent with our hypothesis. The role of CYP2C19 polymorphism in thalidomide treatments remains to be elucidated.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521689</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521688</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Fong, PC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Boss, DS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yap, TA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tutt, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wu, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mergui-Roelvink, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mortimer, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Swaisland, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lau, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">O'Connor, MJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ashworth, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carmichael, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kaye, SB.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Schellens, JH.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">de Bono, JS.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Inhibition of poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase in tumors from BRCA mutation carriers.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The New England journal of medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The New England journal of medicine</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2009</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: The inhibition of poly(adenosine diphosphate [ADP]-ribose) polymerase (PARP) is a potential synthetic lethal therapeutic strategy for the treatment of cancers with specific DNA-repair defects, including those arising in carriers of a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation. We conducted a clinical evaluation in humans of olaparib (AZD2281), a novel, potent, orally active PARP inhibitor.

METHODS: This was a phase 1 trial that included the analysis of pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic characteristics of olaparib. Selection was aimed at having a study population enriched in carriers of a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation.

RESULTS: We enrolled and treated 60 patients; 22 were carriers of a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation and 1 had a strong family history of BRCA-associated cancer but declined to undergo mutational testing. The olaparib dose and schedule were increased from 10 mg daily for 2 of every 3 weeks to 600 mg twice daily continuously. Reversible dose-limiting toxicity was seen in one of eight patients receiving 400 mg twice daily (grade 3 mood alteration and fatigue) and two of five patients receiving 600 mg twice daily (grade 4 thrombocytopenia and grade 3 somnolence). This led us to enroll another cohort, consisting only of carriers of a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation, to receive olaparib at a dose of 200 mg twice daily. Other adverse effects included mild gastrointestinal symptoms. There was no obvious increase in adverse effects seen in the mutation carriers. Pharmacokinetic data indicated rapid absorption and elimination; pharmacodynamic studies confirmed PARP inhibition in surrogate samples (of peripheral-blood mononuclear cells and plucked eyebrow-hair follicles) and tumor tissue. Objective antitumor activity was reported only in mutation carriers, all of whom had ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer and had received multiple treatment regimens.

CONCLUSIONS: Olaparib has few of the adverse effects of conventional chemotherapy, inhibits PARP, and has antitumor activity in cancer associated with the BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation. (ClinicalTrials.gov number, NCT00516373.)</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521688</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521687</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hedlund, PO.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Esposti, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Falkmer, U.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Jacobsson, H.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">DNA as a prognostic marker in advanced high-grade prostatic cancer. A preliminary report. SPCG-I study.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Acta oncologica (Stockholm, Sweden)</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Acta oncologica (Stockholm, Sweden)</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">1991</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">This is a presentation of some preliminary data from SPCG-I, a multicenter study started in 1984 by the Scandinavian Prostatic Cancer Group. It is a randomized double-blind study comparing estramustine phosphate and diethylstilbestrol in the primary treatment of 195 patients with T1-4, NX, M1, G2-3 prostatic cancer. The code is not yet broken. This presentation describes the impact of the pretreatment parameters performance status, pain, tumor burden, grade and DNA-ploidy of the prostate tumor, on time to progression and overall survival. DNA studies have so far only been completed in 66 of the 195 patients. For the whole group of 195 patients, pain (p less than 0.004) and tumor grade (p less than 0.02) had the most significant impact on time to progression, and performance status (p less than 0.01) and grade (p less than 0.03) on overall survival. In the small group of 66 patients where the DNA pattern of the primary tumor was evaluated, no parameter had any significant correlation to time to progression and overall survival. This study is still continuing.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521687</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521686</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Aklillu, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kalow, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Endrenyi, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Harper, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Miura, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ozdemir, V.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">CYP2D6 and DRD2 genes differentially impact pharmacodynamic sensitivity and time course of prolactin response to perphenazine.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pharmacogenetics and genomics</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pharmacogenetics and genomics</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2008</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">OBJECTIVES: We observed that CYP2D6 contributes to pharmacodynamic tissue sensitivity to perphenazine as measured by the areas under the curve (AUCs) expressed as a ratio (prolactin-AUC0-6/perphenazine-AUC0-6) in Chinese Canadians [Pharmacogenetics and Genomics 2007; 17:339-347]. As genetic heterogeneity in drug targets can influence drug response, we sought to further evaluate the contribution of CYP2D6 to pharmacodynamic sensitivity in our previous study sample in tandem with DRD2, the primary molecular target for perphenazine.

METHODS: Genotyping for DRD2 Taq1A, -141C ins/del and Ser311Cys functional polymorphisms was performed using PCR-restriction-fragment length polymorphism methods.

RESULTS: After controlling for DRD2 polymorphisms, CYP2D6 was a significant predictor of pituitary pharmacodynamic tissue sensitivity to perphenazine (P=0.024; power=80.4%). Taq1A polymorphism significantly influenced the time course of prolactin response (P=0.039; power=70%). A1/A1 genotype displayed a higher prolactin elevation 2 h after perphenazine administration (P=0.02). Patients with -141C ins/ins genotype showed a strong trend toward a 38% larger prolactin AUC compared with the -141C ins/del genotypic group (P=0.07).

CONCLUSIONS: CYP2D6 seems to be an independent contributor to pituitary pharmacodynamic tissue sensitivity to perphenazine after accounting for DRD2 functional polymorphisms. The A1 allele of the Taq1A polymorphism was previously shown to decrease D2 receptor density in vitro and in neuroimaging studies in vivo. At a given antipsychotic dose, individuals with A1 allele might thus achieve a higher DRD2 antipsychotic occupancy, which is consistent with an increased prolactin elevation in the A1/A1 genotype in this study. These findings provide a basis for further studies on the endogenous substrates of CYP2D6 and the rational selection of candidate genes for long-term consequences of antipsychotic-induced hyperprolactinemia (e.g. susceptibility to breast and prostate cancers).</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521686</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521685</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mostaghel, EA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cho, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zhang, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Alyamani, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kaipainen, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Green, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Marck, BT.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sharifi, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wright, JL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gulati, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">True, LD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Loda, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Matsumoto, AM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tamae, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Penning, TN.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Balk, SP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kantoff, PW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nelson, PS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Taplin, ME.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Montgomery, RB.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Association of Tissue Abiraterone Levels and </style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">&lt;b&gt;Purpose:&lt;/b&gt;Germline variation in solute carrier organic anion (&lt;i&gt;SLCO&lt;/i&gt;) genes influences cellular steroid uptake and is associated with prostate cancer outcomes. We hypothesized that, due to its steroidal structure, the CYP17A inhibitor abiraterone may undergo transport by&lt;i&gt;SLCO&lt;/i&gt;-encoded transporters and that&lt;i&gt;SLCO&lt;/i&gt;gene variation may influence intracellular abiraterone levels and outcomes.&lt;b&gt;Experimental Design:&lt;/b&gt;Steroid and abiraterone levels were measured in serum and tissue from 58 men with localized prostate cancer in a clinical trial of LHRH agonist plus abiraterone acetate plus prednisone for 24 weeks prior to prostatectomy. Germline DNA was genotyped for 13 SNPs in six&lt;i&gt;SLCO&lt;/i&gt;genes.&lt;b&gt;Results:&lt;/b&gt;Abiraterone levels spanned a broad range (serum median 28 ng/mL, 108 nmol/L; tissue median 77 ng/mL, 271 nmol/L) and were correlated (&lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;= 0.355,&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;= 0.001). Levels correlated positively with steroids upstream of CYP17A (pregnenolone, progesterone), and inversely with steroids downstream of CYP17A (DHEA, AED, testosterone). Serum PSA and tumor volumes were higher in men with undetectable versus detectable tissue abiraterone at prostatectomy (median 0.10 vs. 0.03 ng/dL,&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;= 0.02; 1.28 vs. 0.44 cc,&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;= 0.09, respectively). SNPs in&lt;i&gt;SLCO2B1&lt;/i&gt;associated with significant differences in tissue abiraterone (rs1789693,&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;= 0.0008; rs12422149,&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;= 0.03) and higher rates of minimal residual disease (tumor volume &lt; 0.5 cc; rs1789693, 67% vs. 27%,&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;= 0.009; rs1077858, 46% vs. 0%,&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;= 0.03). LNCaP cells expressing SLCO2B1 showed two- to fourfold higher abiraterone levels compared with vector controls (&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;&lt; 0.05).&lt;b&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/b&gt;Intraprostatic abiraterone levels and genetic variation in&lt;i&gt;SLCO&lt;/i&gt;genes are associated with pathologic responses in high-risk localized prostate cancer. Variation in&lt;i&gt;SLCO&lt;/i&gt;genes may serve as predictors of response to abiraterone treatment.&lt;i&gt;Clin Cancer Res; 23(16); 4592-601. ©2017 AACR&lt;/i&gt;.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521685</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521684</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cheng, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Leibovich, BC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bergstralh, EJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Scherer, BG.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pacelli, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ramnani, DM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zincke, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bostwick, DG.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">p53 alteration in regional lymph node metastases from prostate carcinoma: a marker for progression?</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">1999</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: Alterations of the p53 tumor suppressor gene are associated with advanced stage prostate carcinoma. The biologic significance of p53 nuclear accumulation in prostate cancer patients with regional lymph node metastases is uncertain.

METHODS: The authors investigated p53 alterations by immunohistochemistry in 220 lymph node positive patients who were treated with radical prostatectomy, bilateral pelvic lymphadenectomy, and androgen deprivation therapy between 1987-1992 at the Mayo Clinic. The mean follow-up was 6.3 years. Tumor volume of lymph node metastases was measured using the grid method.

RESULTS: p53 immunoreactivity was detected in 109 of 211 primary tumors (52%) and 83 of 144 matched regional lymph node metastases (58%); this expression was strongly concordant (correlation coefficient 0.53; P = 0.0001). Overexpression of p53 protein in lymph node metastases was associated with distant metastasis free survival by univariate analysis (P = 0.03), but did not reach statistical significance by multivariate analysis (P = 0.07). Regional lymph node cancer volume was the single most important predictor of distant metastases after adjusting for Gleason score, DNA ploidy, and p53 expression.

CONCLUSIONS: The findings of the current study suggest that assessment of biologic changes (including p53 alterations in regional lymph node metastases) could be of value in the assessment of the biologic aggressiveness of prostate carcinoma, whereas p53 expression in the primary tumor does not appear to influence patient outcome.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521684</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521683</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sandhu, SK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Omlin, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hylands, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Miranda, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Barber, LJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Riisnaes, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Reid, AH.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Attard, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chen, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kozarewa, I.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gevensleben, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Campbell, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Fenwick, K.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Assiotis, I.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Olmos, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yap, TA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Fong, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tunariu, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Koh, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Molife, LR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kaye, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lord, CJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ashworth, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">de Bono, J.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) inhibitors for the treatment of advanced germline BRCA2 mutant prostate cancer.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Annals of oncology : official journal of the European Society for Medical Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Annals of oncology : official journal of the European Society for Medical Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2013</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal"/></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521683</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521682</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pantuck, AJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pettaway, CA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dreicer, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Corman, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Katz, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ho, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Aronson, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clark, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Simmons, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Heber, D.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of the effects of pomegranate extract on rising PSA levels in men following primary therapy for prostate cancer.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Prostate cancer and prostatic diseases</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Prostate cancer and prostatic diseases</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2016</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: The primary objective of this study was to compare the effects of pomegranate juice on PSA doubling times (PSADT) in subjects with rising PSA levels after primary therapy for prostate cancer.

METHODS: Double-blind, placebo-controlled multi-institutional study, evaluated the effects of pomegranate liquid extract on serum PSA levels. The primary end point of this study was change in serum PSADT. Additional secondary and exploratory objectives were to evaluate the safety of pomegranate juice and to determine the interaction of manganese superoxide dismutase (MnSOD) AA genotype and pomegranate treatment on PSADT.

RESULTS: One-hundred eighty-three eligible subjects were randomly assigned to the active and placebo groups with a ratio of 2:1 (extract N=102; placebo N=64; juice N=17). The majority of adverse events were of moderate or mild grade. Median PSADT increased from 11.1 months at baseline to 15.6 months in the placebo group (P&lt;0.001) compared with an increase from 12.9 months at baseline to 14.5 months in the extract group (P=0.13) and an increase from 12.7 at baseline to 20.3 in the juice group (P=0.004). However, none of these changes were statistically significant between the three groups (P&gt;0.05). Placebo AA patients experienced a 1.8 month change in median PSADT from 10.9 months at baseline to 12.7 months (P=0.22), while extract patients experienced a 12 month change in median PSADT from 13.6 at baseline to 25.6 months (P=0.03).

CONCLUSIONS: Compared with placebo, pomegranate extract did not significantly prolong PSADT in prostate cancer patients with rising PSA after primary therapy. A significant prolongation in PSADT was observed in both the treatment and placebo arms. Men with the MnSOD AA genotype may represent a group that is more sensitive to the antiproliferative effects of pomegranate on PSADT; however, this finding requires prospective hypothesis testing and validation.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521682</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521681</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Larson, BT.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Magi-Galluzzi, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Casey, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Plummer, SJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Silverman, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Klein, EA.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pathological aggressiveness of prostatic carcinomas related to RNASEL R462Q allelic variants.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The Journal of urology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The Journal of urology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2008</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PURPOSE: Allelic variations in the HPC1/RNASEL gene, especially the R462Q single nucleotide polymorphism, have been associated with increased susceptibility to prostate cancer. Prior studies have suggested that HPC1 or R462Q associated tumors present with more aggressive clinical features. We assessed a series of men undergoing radical prostatectomy for clinical and pathological measures of tumor aggressiveness according to the RNASEL R462Q genotype.

MATERIALS AND METHODS: A prospective analysis of 232 men treated for prostate cancer with radical prostatectomy was performed. Disease aggressiveness at diagnosis was assessed by age at disease onset, biopsy Gleason score, clinical T stage and pretreatment prostate specific antigen. Tumor aggressiveness was assessed pathologically by tumor volume, extraprostatic extension, seminal vesicle involvement and lymph node metastasis. Clinical and pathological characteristics were then correlated with RNASEL genotype.

RESULTS: Of the 232 men studied 104 (45%) were homozygous WT, 101 (43%) were heterozygous and 27 (12%) were homozygous for the R462Q variant, mirroring the distribution in the general population. No significant differences were seen between genotypes in age at disease onset, pretreatment characteristics or pathological features, as assessed by surgical grade and pathological stage. Tumors homozygous for the R462Q variant were of smaller volume than other genotypes (p = 0.02).

CONCLUSIONS: This prospective study suggests that prostate cancer in patients with the R462Q allelic variant of the HPC1/RNASEL gene is not associated with more aggressive clinical or pathological features in radical prostatectomy specimens.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521681</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521680</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Shu, X.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ye, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gu, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">He, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Davis, JW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thompson, TC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Logothetis, CJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kim, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wu, X.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Genetic variants of the Wnt signaling pathway as predictors of aggressive disease and reclassification in men with early stage prostate cancer on active surveillance.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carcinogenesis</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carcinogenesis</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2016</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Little is known about the genetic predictors of prostate cancer aggressiveness and reclassification in men with localized prostate cancer undergoing active surveillance. The Wnt signaling pathway is important for prostate cancer development and progression. Identifying genetic variants associated with prostate cancer aggressiveness and reclassification may have a potential role in the management of localized patients. In this study, we used a three-phase design. In phases I and II prostate cancer patient cohort, 578 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) from 45 genes of the Wnt signaling pathway were analyzed in 1762 localized prostate cancer patients. Twelve SNPs from four regions were significantly associated with aggressive disease, among which, three linked SNPs in CSNK1A1 at 5q32 (represented by rs752822) may differentiate GS 4+3 from GS 3+4 patients (OR = 1.44, 95% CI = 1.12-1.87, P = 4.76×10(-3)). In phase III active surveillance (AS) cohort, genotyping of rs752822 (candidate from phases I and II) and previously identified rs2735839 were determined in 494 GS ≤7 patients. We found a significant association between rs2735839 and prostate cancer reclassification in the AS cohort (AG + AA versus GG, HR = 1.59, 95% CI = 1.11-2.28, P = 0.012) and a suggestive association of rs752822. Jointly, rs752822 and rs2735839 showed good potentials in risk-stratifying GS 7 patients and predicting disease reclassification (OR = 2.71, 95% CI = 1.62-4.51, P = 1×10(-4) in phase II; HR = 1.89, 95% CI = 1.13-3.18, P = 0.016 in phase III). In summary, rs752822 and rs2735839 may assist in risk-stratifying GS 7 patients and predict prostate cancer reclassification. The significant associations were independent from GS, T stage and PSA levels at baseline.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521680</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521679</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">McKay, RR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ye, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Xie, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lis, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Calagua, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zhang, Z.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Trinh, QD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chang, SL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Harshman, LC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ross, AE.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pienta, KJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lin, DW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ellis, WJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Montgomery, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chang, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wagner, AA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bubley, GJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kibel, AS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Taplin, ME.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Evaluation of Intense Androgen Deprivation Before Prostatectomy: A Randomized Phase II Trial of Enzalutamide and Leuprolide With or Without Abiraterone.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2020</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PURPOSE: Patients with locally advanced prostate cancer have an increased risk of cancer recurrence and mortality. In this phase II trial, we evaluate neoadjuvant enzalutamide and leuprolide (EL) with or without abiraterone and prednisone (ELAP) before radical prostatectomy (RP) in men with locally advanced prostate cancer.

PATIENTS AND METHODS: Eligible patients had a biopsy Gleason score of 4 + 3 = 7 or greater, prostate-specific antigen (PSA) greater than 20 ng/mL, or T3 disease (by prostate magnetic resonance imaging). Lymph nodes were required to be smaller than 20 mm. Patients were randomly assigned 2:1 to ELAP or EL for 24 weeks followed by RP. All specimens underwent central pathology review. The primary end point was pathologic complete response or minimal residual disease (residual tumor ≤ 5 mm). Secondary end points were PSA, surgical staging, positive margins, and safety. Biomarkers associated with pathologic outcomes were explored.

RESULTS: Seventy-five patients were enrolled at four centers. Most patients had high-risk disease by National Comprehensive Cancer Network criteria (n = 65; 87%). The pathologic complete response or minimal residual disease rate was 30% (n = 15 of 50) in ELAP-treated patients and 16% (n = four of 25) in EL-treated patients (two-sided P = .263). Rates of ypT3 disease, positive margins, and positive lymph nodes were similar between arms. Treatment was well-tolerated. Residual tumors in the two arms showed comparable levels of ERG, PTEN, androgen receptor PSA, and glucocorticoid receptor expression. Tumor ERG positivity and PTEN loss were associated with more extensive residual tumors at RP.

CONCLUSION: Neoadjuvant hormone therapy followed by RP in locally advanced prostate cancer resulted in favorable pathologic responses in some patients, with a trend toward improved pathologic outcomes with ELAP. Longer follow-up is necessary to evaluate the impact of therapy on recurrence rates. The potential association of ERG and PTEN alterations with worse outcomes warrants additional investigation.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521679</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521678</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gee, JR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Saltzstein, DR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Messing, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kim, K.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kolesar, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Huang, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Havighurst, TC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Harris, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wollmer, BW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Jarrard, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">House, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Parnes, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bailey, HH.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Phase Ib placebo-controlled, tissue biomarker trial of diindolylmethane (BR-DIMNG) in patients with prostate cancer who are undergoing prostatectomy.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">European journal of cancer prevention : the official journal of the European Cancer Prevention Organisation (ECP)</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">European journal of cancer prevention : the official journal of the European Cancer Prevention Organisation (ECP)</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Epidemiologic, preclinical, and early phase I studies of the cruciferous vegetable bioactive metabolite, 3,3'-diindolylmethane (DIM), support its potential prostate cancer chemopreventive ability. We performed a multicenter, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of DIM in patients diagnosed with prostate cancer and scheduled for radical prostatectomy. A total of 45 patients with organ-confined prostate cancer were randomized to 21-28 days of an absorption-enhanced formulation of DIM (BR-DIM) at doses of 100 or 200 mg per os twice daily or to placebo twice daily. Prostate tissue levels of DIM were the primary endpoint, with selected secondary biomarker endpoints including blood levels of DIM, total prostate-specific antigen, testosterone, and the insulin-like growth factor-1: insulin-like growth factor binding protein-3 ratio and the urinary 2-hydroxyestrone/16-hydroxyestrone ratio, obtained at baseline, at day 15, and before surgery, as well as tissue expression of androgen receptor, prostate-specific antigen, Ki67, caspase 3 with cytochrome p450 mRNA expression and genotyping (polymorphisms). DIM was well tolerated with excellent study compliance and relatively rapid accrual of all 45 patients within 1 year. DIM levels were detected in only seven of 28 prostate tissue specimens. There was a statistically significant difference in the change in the urinary 2-hydroxyestrone/16-hydroxyestrone ratio from baseline until before surgery between the placebo and 400 mg DIM groups, with otherwise statistically nonsignificant changes in plasma biomarker expression. The administration of BR-DIM to prostate cancer patients before prostatectomy yields detectable plasma levels but without consistent or significant tissue accumulation or biomarker modulation. This study demonstrates the feasibility of biologic evaluation of relatively nontoxic preventive agents in the preprostatectomy setting with the potential for rapid accrual.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521678</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521677</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Boukovala, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Spetsieris, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Weldon, JA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tsikkinis, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hoang, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Aparicio, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tu, SM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Araujo, JC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zurita, AJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Corn, PG.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pagliaro, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kim, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wang, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Subudhi, SK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tannir, NM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Logothetis, CJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Troncoso, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wen, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Efstathiou, E.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A candidate androgen signalling signature predictive of response to abiraterone acetate in men with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">European journal of cancer (Oxford, England : 1990)</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">European journal of cancer (Oxford, England : 1990)</style></full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Abiraterone acetate</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Androgen receptor</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bone metastasis</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Castration-resistant prostate cancer</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Predictive biomarkers</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2020</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: The unmet need for predictive biomarkers emerged from the unpredictable pattern of response to androgen signalling inhibition in metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer (mCRPC). Here, we report on the testing of a previously identified candidate androgen signalling signature associated with response to androgen signalling inhibition.

PATIENTS AND METHODS: We report on the outcome of the first module of a phase II trial on abiraterone acetate (AA) followed by combination with dasatinib or sunitinib. Bone marrow biopsies (BMBs) with matched bone marrow aspirate and blood samples were collected at baseline and upon progression. End-points included assessment of a prespecified molecular signature consisting of nuclear androgen receptor (AR) overexpression, cytochrome P450, family 17, subfamily A, polypeptide 1 (CYP17) expression, and AR-C-/N terminal expression ratio of ≥0.8 by immunohistochemistry (IHC) in patients with benefit versus primary resistance to AA (i.e. progression within 4 months). Tumour markers also included v-ets avian erythroblastosis virus E26 oncogene homologue (ERG), androgen receptor splice variant (ARV7) by IHC and steroids by liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry.

RESULTS: Of 170 patients accrued from 03/2011 to 02/2015, 44 (26%) were primary resistant to AA. Forty-eight patients had tumour infiltrated BMB at baseline. Pretreatment androgen signalling signature was linked to benefit from AA (p &lt; 0.001). Presence of ERG was associated with benefit (p = 0.05), whereas nuclear ARV7 presence and 20 or more bone lesions at baseline with primary resistance (p = 0.04 and p = 0.0006, respectively).

CONCLUSION: Testing of a prespecified androgen signalling signature was highly supportive of its predictive value in maximal androgen deprivation strategies in mCRPC. Further validation is under way.

TRIAL REGISTRATION: ClinicalTrials.gov NCT01254864.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521677</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521676</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hertz, DL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Owzar, K.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lessans, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wing, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Jiang, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kelly, WK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Patel, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Halabi, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Furukawa, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wheeler, HE.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sibley, AB.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lassiter, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Weisman, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Watson, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Krens, SD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mulkey, F.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Renn, CL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Small, EJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Febbo, PG.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Shterev, I.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kroetz, DL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Friedman, PN.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mahoney, JF.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carducci, MA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kelley, MJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nakamura, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kubo, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dorsey, SG.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dolan, ME.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Morris, MJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ratain, MJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">McLeod, HL.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pharmacogenetic Discovery in CALGB (Alliance) 90401 and Mechanistic Validation of a VAC14 Polymorphism that Increases Risk of Docetaxel-Induced Neuropathy.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PURPOSE: Discovery of SNPs that predict a patient's risk of docetaxel-induced neuropathy would enable treatment individualization to maximize efficacy and avoid unnecessary toxicity. The objectives of this analysis were to discover SNPs associated with docetaxel-induced neuropathy and mechanistically validate these associations in preclinical models of drug-induced neuropathy.

EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN: A genome-wide association study was conducted in metastatic castrate-resistant prostate cancer patients treated with docetaxel, prednisone and randomized to bevacizumab or placebo on CALGB 90401. SNPs were genotyped on the Illumina HumanHap610-Quad platform followed by rigorous quality control. The inference was conducted on the cumulative dose at occurrence of grade 3+ sensory neuropathy using a cause-specific hazard model that accounted for early treatment discontinuation. Genes with SNPs significantly associated with neuropathy were knocked down in cellular and mouse models of drug-induced neuropathy.

RESULTS: A total of 498,081 SNPs were analyzed in 623 Caucasian patients, 50 (8%) of whom experienced grade 3+ neuropathy. The 1,000 SNPs most associated with neuropathy clustered in relevant pathways including neuropathic pain and axonal guidance. An SNP in VAC14 (rs875858) surpassed genome-wide significance (P = 2.12 × 10&lt;sup&gt;-8&lt;/sup&gt;, adjusted P = 5.88 × 10&lt;sup&gt;-7&lt;/sup&gt;). siRNA knockdown of VAC14 in stem cell-derived peripheral neuronal cells increased docetaxel sensitivity as measured by decreased neurite processes (P = 0.0015) and branches (P &lt; 0.0001). Prior to docetaxel treatment, VAC14 heterozygous mice had greater nociceptive sensitivity than wild-type litter mate controls (P = 0.001).

CONCLUSIONS: VAC14 should be prioritized for further validation of its potential role as a predictor of docetaxel-induced neuropathy and biomarker for treatment individualization. Clin Cancer Res; 22(19); 4890-900. ©2016 AACR.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521676</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521675</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Aghajanian, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bell-McGuinn, KM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Burris, HA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Siu, LL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Stayner, LA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wheler, JJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hong, DS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kurkjian, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pant, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Santiago-Walker, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gauvin, JL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Antal, JM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Opalinska, JB.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Morris, SR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Infante, JR.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A phase I, open-label, two-stage study to investigate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics of the oral AKT inhibitor GSK2141795 in patients with solid tumors.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Investigational new drugs</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Investigational new drugs</style></full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Akt</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Endometrial cancer</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">GSK2141795</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PIK3</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PTEN</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Background We sought to determine the recommended phase II dose (RP2D) and schedule of GSK2141795, an oral pan-AKT kinase inhibitor. Patients and Methods Patients with solid tumors were enrolled in the dose-escalation phase. Pharmacokinetic (PK) analysis after a single dose (Cycle 0) informed dose escalation using accelerated dose titration. Once one grade 2 toxicity or dose-limiting toxicity was observed in Cycle 1, the accelerated dose titration was terminated and a 3 + 3 dose escalation was started. Continuous daily dosing was evaluated along with two intermittent regimens (7 days on/7 days off and 3 times per week). In the expansion phase at RP2D, patients with endometrial or prostate cancer, as well as those with select tumor types with a PIK3CA mutation, AKT mutation or PTEN loss, were enrolled. Patients were evaluated for adverse events (AEs), PK parameters, blood glucose and insulin levels, and tumor response. Results The RP2D of GSK2141795 for once-daily dosing is 75 mg. The most common (&gt;10%) treatment-related AEs included diarrhea, fatigue, vomiting, and decreased appetite. Most AEs were low grade. The frequency of hyperglycemia increased with dose; however, at the RP2D, grade 3 hyperglycemia was only reported in 4% of patients and no grade 4 events were observed. PK characteristics were favorable, with a prolonged half-life and low peak-to-trough ratio. There were two partial responses at the RP2D in patients with either a PIK3CA mutation or PTEN loss. Conclusion GSK2141795 was safe and well-tolerated, with clinical activity seen as monotherapy at the RP2D of 75 mg daily. NCT00920257.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521675</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521674</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Creelan, BC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yeh, TC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kim, SW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nogami, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kim, DW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chow, LQM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kanda, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Taylor, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tang, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tang, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Angell, HK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Roudier, MP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Marotti, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gibbons, DL.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A Phase 1 study of gefitinib combined with durvalumab in EGFR TKI-naive patients with EGFR mutation-positive locally advanced/metastatic non-small-cell lung cancer.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">British journal of cancer</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">British journal of cancer</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2021</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs) induce cytolysis and release of tumour proteins, which can stimulate antigen-specific T cells. The safety and efficacy of durvalumab and gefitinib in combination for TKI-naive patients with advanced EGFRm NSCLC was evaluated.

METHODS: This Phase 1 open-label, multicentre trial (NCT02088112) was conducted in 56 patients with NSCLC. Dose expansion permitted TKI-naive patients, primarily with activating L858R or Ex19del EGFRm. Arms 1 + 1a received concurrent therapy; Arm 2 received 4 weeks of gefitinib induction followed by concurrent therapy.

RESULTS: From dose escalation, the recommended dose of durvalumab was 10 mg/kg Q2W with 250 mg QD gefitinib. Pharmacokinetics were as expected, consistent with inhibition of soluble PD-L1 and no treatment-emergent immunogenicity. In dose expansion, 35% of patients had elevated liver enzymes leading to drug discontinuation. In Arms 1 + 1a, objective response rate was 63.3% (95% CI: 43.9-80.1), median progression-free survival (PFS) was 10.1 months (95% CI: 5.5-15.2) and median response duration was 9.2 months (95% CI: 3.7-14.0).

CONCLUSIONS: Durvalumab and gefitinib in combination had higher toxicity than either agent alone. No significant increase in PFS was detected compared with historical controls. Therefore, concurrent PD-L1 inhibitors with gefitinib should be generally avoided in TKI-naive patients with EGFRm NSCLC.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521674</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521673</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wang, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dehm, SM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hillman, DW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sicotte, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tan, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gormley, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bhargava, V.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Jimenez, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Xie, F.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yin, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Qin, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Quevedo, F.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Costello, BA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pitot, HC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ho, T.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bryce, AH.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ye, Z.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Li, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Eiken, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Vedell, PT.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Barman, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">McMenomy, BP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Atwell, TD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carlson, RE.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ellingson, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Eckloff, BW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Qin, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ou, F.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hart, SN.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Huang, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Jen, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wieben, ED.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kalari, KR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Weinshilboum, RM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wang, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kohli, M.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A prospective genome-wide study of prostate cancer metastases reveals association of wnt pathway activation and increased cell cycle proliferation with primary resistance to abiraterone acetate-prednisone.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Annals of oncology : official journal of the European Society for Medical Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Annals of oncology : official journal of the European Society for Medical Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Background: Genomic aberrations have been identified in metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer (mCRPC), but molecular predictors of resistance to abiraterone acetate/prednisone (AA/P) treatment are not known.

Patients and methods: In a prospective clinical trial, mCRPC patients underwent whole-exome sequencing (n = 82) and RNA sequencing (n = 75) of metastatic biopsies before initiating AA/P with the objective of identifying genomic alterations associated with resistance to AA/P. Primary resistance was determined at 12 weeks of treatment using criteria for progression that included serum prostate-specific antigen measurement, bone and computerized tomography imaging and symptom assessments. Acquired resistance was determined using the end point of time to treatment change (TTTC), defined as time from enrollment until change in treatment from progressive disease. Associations of genomic and transcriptomic alterations with primary resistance were determined using logistic regression, Fisher's exact test, single and multivariate analyses. Cox regression models were utilized for determining association of genomic and transcriptomic alterations with TTTC.

Results: At 12 weeks, 32 patients in the cohort had progressed (nonresponders). Median study follow-up was 32.1 months by which time 58 patients had switched treatments due to progression. Median TTTC was 10.1 months (interquartile range: 4.4-24.1). Genes in the Wnt/β-catenin pathway were more frequently mutated and negative regulators of Wnt/β-catenin signaling were more frequently deleted or displayed reduced mRNA expression in nonresponders. Additionally, mRNA expression of cell cycle regulatory genes was increased in nonresponders. In multivariate models, increased cell cycle proliferation scores (≥ 50) were associated with shorter TTTC (hazard ratio = 2.11, 95% confidence interval: 1.17-3.80; P = 0.01).

Conclusions: Wnt/β-catenin pathway activation and increased cell cycle progression scores can serve as molecular markers for predicting resistance to AA/P therapy.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521673</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521672</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Le, DT.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Uram, JN.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wang, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bartlett, BR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kemberling, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Eyring, AD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Skora, AD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Luber, BS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Azad, NS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Laheru, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Biedrzycki, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Donehower, RC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zaheer, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Fisher, GA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Crocenzi, TS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lee, JJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Duffy, SM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Goldberg, RM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">de la Chapelle, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Koshiji, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bhaijee, F.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Huebner, T.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hruban, RH.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wood, LD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cuka, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pardoll, DM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Papadopoulos, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kinzler, KW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zhou, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cornish, TC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Taube, JM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Anders, RA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Eshleman, JR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Vogelstein, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Diaz, LA.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PD-1 Blockade in Tumors with Mismatch-Repair Deficiency.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The New England journal of medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The New England journal of medicine</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2015</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: Somatic mutations have the potential to encode "non-self" immunogenic antigens. We hypothesized that tumors with a large number of somatic mutations due to mismatch-repair defects may be susceptible to immune checkpoint blockade.

METHODS: We conducted a phase 2 study to evaluate the clinical activity of pembrolizumab, an anti-programmed death 1 immune checkpoint inhibitor, in 41 patients with progressive metastatic carcinoma with or without mismatch-repair deficiency. Pembrolizumab was administered intravenously at a dose of 10 mg per kilogram of body weight every 14 days in patients with mismatch repair-deficient colorectal cancers, patients with mismatch repair-proficient colorectal cancers, and patients with mismatch repair-deficient cancers that were not colorectal. The coprimary end points were the immune-related objective response rate and the 20-week immune-related progression-free survival rate.

RESULTS: The immune-related objective response rate and immune-related progression-free survival rate were 40% (4 of 10 patients) and 78% (7 of 9 patients), respectively, for mismatch repair-deficient colorectal cancers and 0% (0 of 18 patients) and 11% (2 of 18 patients) for mismatch repair-proficient colorectal cancers. The median progression-free survival and overall survival were not reached in the cohort with mismatch repair-deficient colorectal cancer but were 2.2 and 5.0 months, respectively, in the cohort with mismatch repair-proficient colorectal cancer (hazard ratio for disease progression or death, 0.10 [P&lt;0.001], and hazard ratio for death, 0.22 [P=0.05]). Patients with mismatch repair-deficient noncolorectal cancer had responses similar to those of patients with mismatch repair-deficient colorectal cancer (immune-related objective response rate, 71% [5 of 7 patients]; immune-related progression-free survival rate, 67% [4 of 6 patients]). Whole-exome sequencing revealed a mean of 1782 somatic mutations per tumor in mismatch repair-deficient tumors, as compared with 73 in mismatch repair-proficient tumors (P=0.007), and high somatic mutation loads were associated with prolonged progression-free survival (P=0.02).

CONCLUSIONS: This study showed that mismatch-repair status predicted clinical benefit of immune checkpoint blockade with pembrolizumab. (Funded by Johns Hopkins University and others; ClinicalTrials.gov number, NCT01876511.).</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521672</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521671</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Winchester, DA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Till, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Goodman, PJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tangen, CM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Santella, RM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Johnson-Pais, TL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Leach, RJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Xu, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zheng, SL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thompson, IM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lucia, MS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lippman, SM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Parnes, HL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Isaacs, WB.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">De Marzo, AM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Drake, CG.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Platz, EA.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Association between variants in genes involved in the immune response and prostate cancer risk in men randomized to the finasteride arm in the Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The Prostate</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The Prostate</style></full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">SNPs</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">finasteride</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">immune genes</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">prostate cancer</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2017</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: We reported that some, but not all single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in select immune response genes are associated with prostate cancer, but not individually with the prevalence of intraprostatic inflammation in the Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial (PCPT) placebo arm. Here, we investigated whether these same SNPs are associated with risk of lower- and higher-grade prostate cancer in men randomized to finasteride, and with prevalence of intraprostatic inflammation among controls. Methods A total of 16 candidate SNPs in IL1β, IL2, IL4, IL6, IL8, IL10, IL12(p40), IFNG, MSR1, RNASEL, TLR4, and TNFA and 7 tagSNPs in IL10 were genotyped in 625 white prostate cancer cases, and 532 white controls negative for cancer on an end-of-study biopsy nested in the PCPT finasteride arm. We used logistic regression to estimate log-additive odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) adjusting for age and family history.

RESULTS: Minor alleles of rs2243250 (T) in IL4 (OR = 1.46, 95% CI 1.03-2.08, P-trend = 0.03), rs1800896 (G) in IL10 (OR = 0.77, 95% CI 0.61-0.96, P-trend = 0.02), rs2430561 (A) in IFNG (OR = 1.33, 95% CI 1.02-1.74; P-trend = 0.04), rs3747531 (C) in MSR1 (OR = 0.55, 95% CI 0.32-0.95; P-trend = 0.03), and possibly rs4073 (A) in IL8 (OR = 0.81, 95% CI 0.64-1.01, P-trend = 0.06) were associated with higher- (Gleason 7-10; N = 222), but not lower- (Gleason 2-6; N = 380) grade prostate cancer. In men with low PSA (&lt;2 ng/mL), these higher-grade disease associations were attenuated and/or no longer significant, whereas associations with higher-grade disease were apparent for minor alleles of rs1800795 (C: OR = 0.70, 95% CI 0.51-0.94, P-trend = 0.02) and rs1800797 (A: OR = 0.72, 95% CI 0.53-0.98, P-trend = 0.04) in IL6. While some IL10 tagSNPs were associated with lower- and higher-grade prostate cancer, distributions of IL10 haplotypes did not differ, except possibly between higher-grade cases and controls among those with low PSA (P = 0.07). We did not observe an association between the studied SNPs and intraprostatic inflammation in the controls.

CONCLUSION: In the PCPT finasteride arm, variation in genes involved in the immune response, including possibly IL8 and IL10 as in the placebo arm, may be associated with prostate cancer, especially higher-grade disease, but not with intraprostatic inflammation. We cannot rule out PSA-associated detection bias or chance due to multiple testing.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521671</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521670</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Meade, AD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Maguire, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bryant, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cullen, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Medipally, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">White, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">McClean, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Shields, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Armstrong, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dunne, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Noone, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bradshaw, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Finn, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Shannon, AM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Howe, O.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lyng, FM.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Prediction of DNA damage and G2 chromosomal radio-sensitivity ex vivo in peripheral blood mononuclear cells with label-free Raman micro-spectroscopy.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">International journal of radiation biology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">International journal of radiation biology</style></full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">DNA damage</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">G2 radiosensitivity</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Raman spectroscopy</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">individual radiation sensitivity</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">partial least squares regression</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">support vector regression</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">γH2AX fluorescence</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2019</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PURPOSE: Liquid biopsies are a potentially rich store of biochemical information that can be linked to an individual's response to therapeutic treatments, including radiotherapy, and which may ultimately play a role in the individualization of treatment regimens. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) can be used not only for the biochemical profiling of the individual, but also, being living cells, can provide insights into the individuals response to ionizing radiation exposure.

MATERIALS AND METHODS: The present study attempts to link the biochemical profile of lymphocytes within PBMCs obtained through Raman spectroscopy to in vitro measures of low-dose (&lt;0.5Gy) DNA damage response and cytogenetic metrics of radiosensitivity in a cohort of healthy controls and prostate cancer patients (from CTRIAL-IE(ICORG) 08-17, NCT00951535). All parallel metrics to the Raman spectra of the cells were obtained ex vivo in cycling peripheral blood lymphocytes, with radiosensitivity estimated using the G2 chromosomal assay and DNA damage assessed using γH2AX fluorescence. Spectra from a total of 26 healthy volunteers and 22 prostate cancer patients were obtained.

RESULTS: The links between both measures of cellular response to ionizing radiation and the Raman spectra were modeled using partial least squares regression (PLSR) and support-vector regression (SVR). It was found that neither regression approach could predict radiation-induced G2 score well, but could predict γH2AX MFI with the SVR outperforming PLSR, implying a non-linear relationship between spectral measurements and measures of DNA damage.

CONCLUSIONS: Raman spectroscopy of PBMCs represents a label-free approach for prediction of DNA damage levels for either prospective or retrospective analysis.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521670</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521669</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dai, JY.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">LeBlanc, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Goodman, PJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lucia, MS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thompson, IM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tangen, CM.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Case-only Methods Identified Genetic Loci Predicting a Subgroup of Men with Reduced Risk of High-grade Prostate Cancer by Finasteride.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer prevention research (Philadelphia, Pa.)</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer prevention research (Philadelphia, Pa.)</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2019</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">In the Prostate Cancer Prevention Trial (PCPT), genotypes that may modify the effect of finasteride on the risk of prostate cancer have not been identified. Germline genetic data from 1,157 prostate cancer cases in PCPT were analyzed by case-only methods. Genotypes included 357 SNPs from 83 candidate genes in androgen metabolism, inflammation, circadian rhythm, and other pathways. Univariate case-only analysis was conducted to evaluate whether individual SNPs modified the finasteride effect on the risk of high-grade and low-grade prostate cancer. Case-only classification trees and random forests, which are powerful machine learning methods with resampling-based controls for model complexity, were employed to identify a predictive signature for genotype-specific treatment effects. Accounting for multiple testing, a single SNP in&lt;i&gt;SRD5A1&lt;/i&gt;gene (rs472402) significantly modified the finasteride effect on high-grade prostate cancer (Gleason score &gt; 6) in PCPT (family-wise error rate &lt; 0.05). Men carrying GG genotype at this locus had a 55% reduction of the risk in developing high-grade cancer when assigned to finasteride (RR = 0.45; 95% confidence interval, 0.27-0.75). Additional effect-modifying SNPs with moderate statistical significance were identified by case-only trees and random forests. A prediction model built by the case-only random forest method with 28 selected SNPs classified 37% of PCPT men to have reduced risk of high-grade prostate cancer when taking finasteride, while the others have increased risk. In conclusion, case-only methods identified SNPs that modified the effect of finasteride on the risk of high-grade prostate cancer and predicted a subgroup of men who had reduced cancer risk by finasteride.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521669</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521668</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mateo, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ganji, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lemech, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Burris, HA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Han, SW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Swales, K.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Decordova, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">DeYoung, MP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Smith, DA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kalyana-Sundaram, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wu, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Motwani, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kumar, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tolson, JM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rha, SY.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chung, HC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Eder, JP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sharma, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bang, YJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Infante, JR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yan, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">de Bono, JS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Arkenau, HT.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A First-Time-in-Human Study of GSK2636771, a Phosphoinositide 3 Kinase Beta-Selective Inhibitor, in Patients with Advanced Solid Tumors.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">&lt;b&gt;Background:&lt;/b&gt;The PI3K/protein kinase B (AKT) pathway is commonly activated in several tumor types. Selective targeting of p110β could result in successful pathway inhibition while avoiding the on- and off-target effects of pan-PI3K inhibitors. GSK2636771 is a potent, orally bioavailable, adenosine triphosphate-competitive, selective inhibitor of PI3Kβ.&lt;b&gt;Methods:&lt;/b&gt;We evaluated the safety, pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics and antitumor activity of GSK2636771 to define the recommended phase II dose (RP2D). During the dose-selection and dose-escalation stages (parts 1 and 2), patients with&lt;i&gt;PTEN&lt;/i&gt;-deficient advanced solid tumors received escalating doses of GSK2636771 (25-500 mg once daily) using a modified 3+3 design to determine the RP2D; tumor type-specific expansion cohorts (part 3) were implemented to further assess tumor responses at the RP2D.&lt;b&gt;Results:&lt;/b&gt;A total of 65 patients were enrolled; dose-limiting toxicities were hypophosphatemia and hypocalcemia. Adverse events included diarrhea (48%), nausea (40%), and vomiting (31%). Single- and repeat-dose exposure increased generally dose proportionally. GSK2636771 400 mg once daily was the RP2D. Phospho/total AKT ratio decreased with GSK2636771 in tumor and surrogate tissue. A castrate-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC) patient harboring&lt;i&gt;PIK3CB&lt;/i&gt;amplification had a partial response for over a year; an additional 10 patients derived durable (≥24 weeks) clinical benefit, including two other patients with CRPC with&lt;i&gt;PIK3CB&lt;/i&gt;alterations (≥34 weeks). GSK2636771 400 mg once daily orally induced sufficient exposure and target inhibition with a manageable safety profile.&lt;b&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/b&gt;Genomic aberrations of&lt;i&gt;PIK3CB&lt;/i&gt;may be associated with clinical benefit from GSK2636771.&lt;i&gt;Clin Cancer Res; 23(19); 5981-92. ©2017 AACR&lt;/i&gt;.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521668</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521667</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Werner, TL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sachdev, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Swisher, EM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gutierrez, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kittaneh, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Stein, MN.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Xiong, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dunbar, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sullivan, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Komarnitsky, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">McKee, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tan, AR.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Safety and pharmacokinetics of veliparib extended-release in patients with advanced solid tumors: a phase I study.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer medicine</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer medicine</style></full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">

BRCA

</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PARP inhibitor</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">breast carcinoma</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">extended-release formulation</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">ovarian carcinoma</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">veliparib</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase-1/2 inhibitor veliparib is active against tumors deficient in homologous DNA damage repair. The pharmacokinetics and safety of veliparib extended-release (ER) were evaluated in patients with advanced solid tumors. This phase I study assessed veliparib-ER up to 800 mg once daily or 600 mg twice daily. Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs), recommended phase II dose (RP2D), and maximum tolerated dose (MTD) were assessed in cycle 1 and safety/tolerability during continuous administration (28-day cycles). Seventy-one patients (n = 53 ovarian, n = 17 breast, n = 1 prostate carcinoma) received veliparib; 50 had deleterious breast cancer susceptibility (BRCA) gene mutations. Single-dose veliparib-ER 200 mg (fasting) led to 58% lower peak concentration and similar area under the concentration-time curve compared with veliparib immediate-release (IR). Three patients experienced DLTs (grade 2: asthenia; grade 3: nausea/vomiting, seizure). RP2D and MTD for veliparib-ER were 400 mg BID. The most frequent adverse events (AEs) were nausea (78.9%) and vomiting (50.7%). The most common grade 3/4 treatment-related AEs were as follows: thrombocytopenia (7.0%), nausea, and anemia (4.2% each). Overall, 12 (27.3%) patients with ovarian and 10 (62.5%) patients with breast carcinoma had a partial response. Veliparib-ER, versus veliparib-IR, exhibited an improved pharmacokinetic profile and was well tolerated in patients with ovarian and BRCA-mutated breast cancers.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521667</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521666</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ahmed, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Goh, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Saunders, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cieza-Borrella, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kote-Jarai, Z.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Schumacher, FR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Eeles, R.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Germline genetic variation in prostate susceptibility does not predict outcomes in the chemoprevention trials PCPT and SELECT.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Prostate cancer and prostatic diseases</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Prostate cancer and prostatic diseases</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2021</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: The development of prostate cancer can be influenced by genetic and environmental factors. Numerous germline SNPs influence prostate cancer susceptibility. The functional pathways in which these SNPs increase prostate cancer susceptibility are unknown. Finasteride is currently not being used routinely as a chemoprevention agent but the long term outcomes of the PCPT trial are awaited. The outcomes of the SELECT trial have not recommended the use of chemoprevention in preventing prostate cancer. This study investigated whether germline risk SNPs could be used to predict outcomes in the PCPT and SELECT trial.

METHODS: Genotyping was performed in European men entered into the PCPT trial (n = 2434) and SELECT (n = 4885). Next generation genotyping was performed using Affymetrix® Eureka™ Genotyping protocols. Logistic regression models were used to test the association of risk scores and the outcomes in the PCPT and SELECT trials.

RESULTS: Of the 100 SNPs, 98 designed successfully and genotyping was validated for samples genotyped on other platforms. A number of SNPs predicted for aggressive disease in both trials. Men with a higher polygenic score are more likely to develop prostate cancer in both trials, but the score did not predict for other outcomes in the trial.

CONCLUSION: Men with a higher polygenic risk score are more likely to develop prostate cancer. There were no interactions of these germline risk SNPs and the chemoprevention agents in the SELECT and PCPT trials.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521666</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521665</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Martinez, EE.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Darke, AK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tangen, CM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Goodman, PJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Fowke, JH.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Klein, EA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Abdulkadir, SA.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A functional variant in NKX3.1 associated with prostate cancer risk in the Selenium and Vitamin E Cancer Prevention Trial (SELECT).</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer prevention research (Philadelphia, Pa.)</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer prevention research (Philadelphia, Pa.)</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2015</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">NKX3.1 is an androgen-regulated prostate tumor suppressor protein. We previously found that antioxidant administration (N-acetylcysteine) in the Nkx3.1 knockout mouse model promoted prostate epithelial proliferation, suggesting that NKX3.1 activity modifies the effect of antioxidant administration on prostate carcinogenesis. Interestingly, administration of the antioxidant vitamin E significantly increased prostate cancer risk in the Selenium and Vitamin E Cancer Prevention Trial (SELECT), suggesting that our animal experiments may be relevant to humans. To determine whether NKX3.1 played a role in increased human prostate cancer risk associated with antioxidant administration in SELECT, we investigated the joint risk of antioxidant administration and NKX3.1 genotypes previously found to be associated with decreased NKX3.1 mRNA expression (rs11781886) or DNA-binding activity in vitro (rs2228013) in the SELECT biomarker case-cohort substudy (1,866 cases; 3,135 non-cases). Multivariable COX regression models were developed to determine the joint association of NKX3.1 genotypes with administration of vitamin E, selenium, or the combination, compared with placebo. The CC genotype at rs11781886 combined with selenium administration was associated with increased overall prostate cancer risk [HR, 1.676; 95% confidence interval (CI), 1.011-2.777; P = 0.045] and low-grade prostate cancer risk (HR, 1.811; 95% CI, 1.016-3.228; P = 0.0441). Similarly, the rs11781886 minor allele (CC+CT) combined with vitamin E administration was significantly associated with increased prostate cancer risk (HR, 1.450; 95% CI, 1.117-1.882; P = 0.0052). Our results indicate that variation in NKX3.1 expression combined with selenium or vitamin E treatment modifies the risk of prostate cancer. Genetic background may modulate the effects of antioxidant supplementation thought to act as chemoprevention agents.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521665</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521664</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chen, EJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sowalsky, AG.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gao, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cai, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Voznesensky, O.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Schaefer, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Loda, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">True, LD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ye, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Troncoso, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lis, RL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kantoff, PW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Montgomery, RB.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nelson, PS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bubley, GJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Balk, SP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Taplin, ME.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Abiraterone treatment in castration-resistant prostate cancer selects for progesterone responsive mutant androgen receptors.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2016</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PURPOSE: The CYP17A1 inhibitor abiraterone markedly reduces androgen precursors and is thereby effective in castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC). However, abiraterone increases progesterone, which can activate certain mutant androgen receptors (AR) identified previously in flutamide-resistant tumors. Therefore, we sought to determine if CYP17A1 inhibitor treatment selects for progesterone-activated mutant ARs.

EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN: AR was examined by targeted sequencing in metastatic tumor biopsies from 18 patients with CRPC who were progressing on a CYP17A1 inhibitor (17 on abiraterone, 1 on ketoconazole), alone or in combination with dutasteride, and by whole-exome sequencing in residual tumor in one patient treated with neoadjuvant leuprolide plus abiraterone.

RESULTS: The progesterone-activated T878A-mutant AR was present at high allele frequency in 3 of the 18 CRPC cases. It was also present in one focus of resistant tumor in the neoadjuvant-treated patient, but not in a second clonally related resistant focus that instead had lost one copy of PTEN and both copies of CHD1. The T878A mutation appeared to be less common in the subset of patients with CRPC treated with abiraterone plus dutasteride, and transfection studies showed that dutasteride was a more potent direct antagonist of the T878A versus the wild-type AR.

CONCLUSIONS: These findings indicate that selection for tumor cells expressing progesterone-activated mutant ARs is a mechanism of resistance to CYP17A1 inhibition.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521664</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521663</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Fumet, JD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Limagne, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thibaudin, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Truntzer, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bertaut, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rederstorff, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ghiringhelli, F.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Precision medicine phase II study evaluating the efficacy of a double immunotherapy by durvalumab and tremelimumab combined with olaparib in patients with solid cancers and carriers of homologous recombination repair genes mutation in response or stable after olaparib treatment.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BMC cancer</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BMC cancer</style></full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Durvalumab</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Homologous repair</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Immune checkpoint inhibitors</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Olaparib</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PARP inhibitors</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tremelilumab</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2020</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: Tumors with deficient homologous repair are sensitive to PARP inhibitors such as olaparib which is known to have immunogenic properties. Durvalumab (D) is a human monoclonal antibody (mAb) which inhibits binding of programmed cell death ligand 1 (PD-L1) to its receptor. Tremelimumab (T) is a mAb directed against the cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated protein 4 (CTLA-4). This study is designed to evaluate the efficacy of combination of olaparib, durvalumab and tremelimumab in patients with a solid tumors with a mutation in homologous gene repair.

METHODS: This phase II study will assess the efficacy and safety of olaparib/D/T association in patients (n = 213) with several types of solid cancers (breast cancer, ovarian cancer, pancreatic cancer, endometrial cancer, prostate cancer and others) with at least one mutation in homologous repair genes (BRCA1, BRCA2, PALB2, ATM, FANCA, FANCB, FANCC, FANCE, FANCF, CHEK2, RAD51, BARD1, MRE11, RAD50, NBS1, HDAC2), LKB1/STK11, INPP4B, STAG2, ERG, CHEK1, BLM, LIG4, ATR, ATRX, CDK12). Good performance status patients and corresponding to specific inclusion criteria of each cohort will be eligible. STEP1: Patients will receive olaparib 300 mg BID. In absence of progression after 6 weeks of olaparib, they will follow STEP 2 with olaparib and immunotherapy by durvalumab (1500 mg Q4W) + tremelimumab (75 mg IV Q4W) during 4 months and will further pursue durvalumab alone until disease progression, death, intolerable toxicity, or patient/investigator decision to stop (for a maximum duration of 24 months, and 36 months for ovarian cohort). Primary endpoint is safety and efficacy according to progression-free survival (PFS) of olaparib + immunotherapy (durvalumab + tremelimumab) during 4 months followed by durvalumab alone as maintenance in patients with solid cancers and in response or stable, after prior molecular target therapy by olaparib; secondary endpoints include overall survival (OS), disease control rate (DCR), response rate after 6 weeks of olaparib, safety of olaparib/durvalumab/tremelimumab association. Blood, plasma and tumor tissue will be collected for potential prognostic and predictive biomarkers.

DISCUSSION: This study is the first trial to test the combination of olaparib and double immunotherapy based on molecular screening.

TRIAL REGISTRATION: NCT04169841 , date of registration November 20, 2019.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521663</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521662</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Fachal, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gómez-Caamaño, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Barnett, GC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Peleteiro, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carballo, AM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Calvo-Crespo, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kerns, SL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sánchez-García, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lobato-Busto, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dorling, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Elliott, RM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dearnaley, DP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sydes, MR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hall, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Burnet, NG.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carracedo, Á.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rosenstein, BS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">West, CM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dunning, AM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Vega, A.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A three-stage genome-wide association study identifies a susceptibility locus for late radiotherapy toxicity at 2q24.1.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nature genetics</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nature genetics</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2015</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">There is increasing evidence supporting the role of genetic variants in the development of radiation-induced toxicity. However, previous candidate gene association studies failed to elucidate the common genetic variation underlying this phenotype, which could emerge years after the completion of treatment. We performed a genome-wide association study on a Spanish cohort of 741 individuals with prostate cancer treated with external beam radiotherapy (EBRT). The replication cohorts consisted of 633 cases from the UK and 368 cases from North America. One locus comprising TANC1 (lowest unadjusted P value for overall late toxicity=6.85×10(-9), odds ratio (OR)=6.61, 95% confidence interval (CI)=2.23-19.63) was replicated in the second stage (lowest unadjusted P value for overall late toxicity=2.08×10(-4), OR=6.17, 95% CI=2.25-16.95; Pcombined=4.16×10(-10)). The inclusion of the third cohort gave unadjusted Pcombined=4.64×10(-11). These results, together with the role of TANC1 in regenerating damaged muscle, suggest that the TANC1 locus influences the development of late radiation-induced damage.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521662</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521661</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hearn, JWD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sweeney, CJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Almassi, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Reichard, CA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Reddy, CA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Li, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hobbs, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Jarrard, DF.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chen, YH.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dreicer, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Garcia, JA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carducci, MA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">DiPaola, RS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sharifi, N.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">HSD3B1 Genotype and Clinical Outcomes in Metastatic Castration-Sensitive Prostate Cancer.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">JAMA oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">JAMA oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2020</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Importance: The adrenal-restrictive HSD3B1(1245A) allele limits extragonadal dihydrotestosterone synthesis, whereas the adrenal-permissive HSD3B1(1245C) allele augments extragonadal dihydrotestosterone synthesis. Retrospective studies have suggested an association between the adrenal-permissive allele, the frequency of which is highest in white men, and early development of castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC).

Objective: To examine the association between the adrenal-permissive HSD3B1(1245C) allele and early development of CRPC using prospective data.

Design, Setting, and Participants: The E3805 Chemohormonal Therapy vs Androgen Ablation Randomized Trial for Extensive Disease in Prostate Cancer (CHAARTED) was a large, multicenter, phase 3 trial of castration with or without docetaxel treatment in men with newly diagnosed metastatic prostate cancer. From July 28, 2006, through December 31, 2012, 790 patients underwent randomization, of whom 527 had available DNA samples. In this study, the HSD3B1 germline genotype was retrospectively determined in 475 white men treated in E3805 CHAARTED, and clinical outcomes were analyzed by genotype. Data analysis was performed from July 28, 2006, to October 17, 2018.

Interventions: Men were randomized to castration plus docetaxel, 75 mg/m2, every 3 weeks for 6 cycles or castration alone.

Main Outcomes and Measures: Two-year freedom from CRPC and 5-year overall survival, with results stratified by disease volume. Patients were combined across study arms according to genotype to assess the overall outcome associated with genotype. Secondary analyses by treatment arm evaluated whether the docetaxel outcome varied with genotype.

Results: Of 475 white men with DNA samples, 270 patients (56.8%) inherited the adrenal-permissive genotype (≥1 HSD3B1[1245C] allele). Mean (SD) age was 63 (8.7) years. Freedom from CRPC at 2 years was diminished in men with low-volume disease with the adrenal-permissive vs adrenal-restrictive genotype: 51.0% (95% CI, 40.9%-61.2%) vs 70.5% (95% CI, 60.0%-80.9%) (P = .01). Overall survival at 5 years was also worse in men with low-volume disease with the adrenal-permissive genotype: 57.5% (95% CI, 47.4%-67.7%) vs 70.8% (95% CI, 60.3%-81.3%) (P = .03). Hazard ratios were 1.89 (95% CI, 1.13-3.14; P = .02) for CRPC and 1.74 (95% CI, 1.01-3.00; P = .045) for death. There was no association between genotype and outcomes in men with high-volume disease. There was no interaction between genotype and benefit from docetaxel.

Conclusions and Relevance: Inheritance of the adrenal-permissive HSD3B1 genotype is associated with earlier castration resistance and shorter overall survival in men with low-volume metastatic prostate cancer and may help identify men more likely to benefit from escalated androgen receptor axis inhibition beyond gonadal testosterone suppression.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521661</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521660</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Feng, FY.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Huang, HC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Spratt, DE.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zhao, SG.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sandler, HM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Simko, JP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Davicioni, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nguyen, PL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pollack, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Efstathiou, JA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dicker, AP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Todorovic, T.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Margrave, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Liu, YS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dabbas, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thompson, DJS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Das, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dignam, JJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sweeney, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Attard, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bahary, JP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lukka, HR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hall, WA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pisansky, TM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Shah, AB.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pugh, SL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Shipley, WU.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tran, PT.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Validation of a 22-Gene Genomic Classifier in Patients With Recurrent Prostate Cancer: An Ancillary Study of the NRG/RTOG 9601 Randomized Clinical Trial.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">JAMA oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">JAMA oncology</style></full-title></periodical><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Importance: Decipher (Decipher Biosciences Inc) is a genomic classifier (GC) developed to estimate the risk of distant metastasis (DM) after radical prostatectomy (RP) in patients with prostate cancer.

Objective: To validate the GC in the context of a randomized phase 3 trial.

Design, Setting, and Participants: This ancillary study used RP specimens from the phase 3 placebo-controlled NRG/RTOG 9601 randomized clinical trial conducted from March 1998 to March 2003. The specimens were centrally reviewed, and RNA was extracted from the highest-grade tumor available in 2019 with a median follow-up of 13 years. Clinical-grade whole transcriptomes from samples passing quality control were assigned GC scores (scale, 0-1). A National Clinical Trials Network-approved prespecified statistical plan included the primary objective of validating the independent prognostic ability of GC for DM, with secondary end points of prostate cancer-specific mortality (PCSM) and overall survival (OS). Data were analyzed from September 2019 to December 2019.

Intervention: Salvage radiotherapy (sRT) with or without 2 years of bicalutamide.

Main Outcomes and Measures: The preplanned primary end point of this study was the independent association of the GC with the development of DM.

Results: In this ancillary study of specimens from a phase 3 randomized clinical trial, GC scores were generated from 486 of 760 randomized patients with a median follow-up of 13 years; samples from a total of 352 men (median [interquartile range] age, 64.5 (60-70) years; 314 White [89.2%] participants) passed microarray quality control and comprised the final cohort for analysis. On multivariable analysis, the GC (continuous variable, per 0.1 unit) was independently associated with DM (hazard ratio [HR], 1.17; 95% CI, 1.05-1.32; P = .006), PCSM (HR, 1.39; 95% CI, 1.20-1.63; P &lt; .001), and OS (HR, 1.17; 95% CI, 1.06-1.29; P = .002) after adjusting for age, race/ethnicity, Gleason score, T stage, margin status, entry prostate-specific antigen, and treatment arm. Although the original planned analysis was not powered to detect a treatment effect interaction by GC score, the estimated absolute effect of bicalutamide on 12-year OS was less when comparing patients with lower vs higher GC scores (2.4% vs 8.9%), which was further demonstrated in men receiving early sRT at a prostate-specific antigen level lower than 0.7 ng/mL (-7.8% vs 4.6%).

Conclusions and Relevance: This ancillary validation study of the Decipher GC in a randomized trial cohort demonstrated association of the GC with DM, PCSM, and OS independent of standard clinicopathologic variables. These results suggest that not all men with biochemically recurrent prostate cancer after surgery benefit equally from the addition of hormone therapy to sRT.

Trial Registration: ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT00002874.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521660</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521659</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kolinsky, MP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rescigno, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bianchini, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zafeiriou, Z.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mehra, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mateo, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Michalarea, V.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Riisnaes, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Crespo, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Figueiredo, I.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Miranda, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nava Rodrigues, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Flohr, P.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tunariu, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Banerji, U.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ruddle, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sharp, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Welti, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lambros, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carreira, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Raynaud, FI.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Swales, KE.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Plymate, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Luo, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tovey, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Porta, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Slade, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Leonard, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hall, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">de Bono, JS.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A phase I dose-escalation study of enzalutamide in combination with the AKT inhibitor AZD5363 (capivasertib) in patients with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Annals of oncology : official journal of the European Society for Medical Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Annals of oncology : official journal of the European Society for Medical Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">AKT inhibitor</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">AZD5363</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">biomarkers</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">capivasertib</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">enzalutamide</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">prostate cancer</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2021</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: Activation of the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway through loss of phosphatase and tensin homolog (PTEN) occurs in approximately 50% of patients with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer (mCRPC). Recent evidence suggests that combined inhibition of the androgen receptor (AR) and AKT may be beneficial in mCRPC with PTEN loss.

PATIENTS AND METHODS: mCRPC patients who previously failed abiraterone and/or enzalutamide, received escalating doses of AZD5363 (capivasertib) starting at 320 mg twice daily (b.i.d.) given 4 days on and 3 days off, in combination with enzalutamide 160 mg daily. The co-primary endpoints were safety/tolerability and determining the maximum tolerated dose and recommended phase II dose; pharmacokinetics, antitumour activity, and exploratory biomarker analysis were also evaluated.

RESULTS: Sixteen patients were enrolled, 15 received study treatment and 13 were assessable for dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs). Patients were treated at 320, 400, and 480 mg b.i.d. dose levels of capivasertib. The recommended phase II dose identified for capivasertib was 400 mg b.i.d. with 1/6 patients experiencing a DLT (maculopapular rash) at this level. The most common grade ≥3 adverse events were hyperglycemia (26.7%) and rash (20%). Concomitant administration of enzalutamide significantly decreased plasma exposure of capivasertib, though this did not appear to impact pharmacodynamics. Three patients met the criteria for response (defined as prostate-specific antigen decline ≥50%, circulating tumour cell conversion, and/or radiological response). Responses were seen in patients with PTEN loss or activating mutations in AKT, low or absent AR-V7 expression, as well as those with an increase in phosphorylated extracellular signal-regulated kinase (pERK) in post-exposure samples.

CONCLUSIONS: The combination of capivasertib and enzalutamide is tolerable and has antitumour activity, with all responding patients harbouring aberrations in the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway.

CLINICAL TRIAL NUMBER: NCT02525068.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521659</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521658</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Moore, SC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Leitzmann, MF.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Weinstein, SJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Snyder, K.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Albanes, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Virtamo, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Graubard, BI.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mayne, ST.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yu, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Peters, U.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gunter, MJ.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Insulin resistance-related gene polymorphisms and risk of prostate cancer.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer epidemiology, biomarkers &amp; prevention : a publication of the American Association for Cancer Research, cosponsored by the American Society of Preventive Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer epidemiology, biomarkers &amp; prevention : a publication of the American Association for Cancer Research, cosponsored by the American Society of Preventive Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2007</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal"/></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521658</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521657</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Beltran, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Oromendia, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Danila, DC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Montgomery, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hoimes, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Szmulewitz, RZ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Vaishampayan, U.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Armstrong, AJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Stein, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pinski, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mosquera, JM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sailer, V.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bareja, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Romanel, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gumpeni, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sboner, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dardenne, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Puca, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Prandi, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rubin, MA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Scher, HI.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rickman, DS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Demichelis, F.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nanus, DM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ballman, KV.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tagawa, ST.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A Phase II Trial of the Aurora Kinase A Inhibitor Alisertib for Patients with Castration-resistant and Neuroendocrine Prostate Cancer: Efficacy and Biomarkers.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2019</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PURPOSE: Neuroendocrine prostate cancer (NEPC) is an aggressive variant of prostate cancer that may develop&lt;i&gt;de novo&lt;/i&gt;or as a mechanism of treatment resistance. N-myc is capable of driving NEPC progression. Alisertib inhibits the interaction between N-myc and its stabilizing factor Aurora-A, inhibiting N-myc signaling, and suppressing tumor growth.

PATIENTS AND METHODS: Sixty men were treated with alisertib 50 mg twice daily for 7 days every 21 days. Eligibility included metastatic prostate cancer and at least one: small-cell neuroendocrine morphology; ≥50% neuroendocrine marker expression; new liver metastases without PSA progression; or elevated serum neuroendocrine markers. The primary endpoint was 6-month radiographic progression-free survival (rPFS). Pretreatment biopsies were evaluated by whole exome and RNA-seq and patient-derived organoids were developed.

RESULTS: Median PSA was 1.13 ng/mL (0.01-514.2), number of prior therapies was 3, and 68% had visceral metastases. Genomic alterations involved&lt;i&gt;RB1&lt;/i&gt;(55%),&lt;i&gt;TP53&lt;/i&gt;(46%),&lt;i&gt;PTEN&lt;/i&gt;(29%),&lt;i&gt;BRCA2&lt;/i&gt;(29%), and&lt;i&gt;AR&lt;/i&gt;(27%), and there was a range of androgen receptor signaling and NEPC marker expression. Six-month rPFS was 13.4% and median overall survival was 9.5 months (7.3-13). Exceptional responders were identified, including complete resolution of liver metastases and prolonged stable disease, with tumors suggestive of N-myc and Aurora-A overactivity. Patient organoids exhibited concordant responses to alisertib and allowed for the dynamic testing of Aurora-N-myc complex disruption.

CONCLUSIONS: Although the study did not meet its primary endpoint, a subset of patients with advanced prostate cancer and molecular features supporting Aurora-A and N-myc activation achieved significant clinical benefit from single-agent alisertib.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521657</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521656</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Anastasopoulou, EA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Voutsas, IF.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Keramitsoglou, T.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gouttefangeas, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kalbacher, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thanos, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Papamichail, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Perez, SA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Baxevanis, CN.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A pilot study in prostate cancer patients treated with the AE37 Ii-key-HER-2/neu polypeptide vaccine suggests that HLA-A*24 and HLA-DRB1*11 alleles may be prognostic and predictive biomarkers for clinical benefit.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer immunology, immunotherapy : CII</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer immunology, immunotherapy : CII</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2015</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Recently, several types of immunotherapies have been shown to induce encouraging clinical results, though in a restricted number of patients. Consequently, there is a need to identify immune biomarkers to select patients who will benefit from such therapies. Such predictive biomarkers may be also used as surrogates for overall survival (OS). We have recently found correlations between immunologic parameters and clinical outcome in prostate cancer patients who had been vaccinated with a HER-2/neu hybrid polypeptide vaccine (AE37) and received one booster 6 months post-primary vaccinations. Herein, we aimed to expand these retrospective analyses by studying the predictive impact of HLA-A*24 and HLA-DRB1*11 alleles, which are expressed at high frequencies among responders in our vaccinated patients, for clinical and immunological responses to AE37 vaccination. Our data show an increased OS of patients expressing the HLA-DRB1*11 or HLA-A*24 alleles, or both. Vaccine-induced immunological responses, measured as interferon γ (IFN-γ) responses in vitro or delayed-type hypersensitivity reactions in vivo, were also higher in these patients and inversely correlated with suppressor elements. Preexisting (i.e., before vaccinations with AE37) levels of vaccine-specific IFN-γ immunity and plasma TGF-β, among the HLA-A*24 and/or HLA-DRB1*11 positive patients, were strong indicators for immunological responses to AE37 treatment. These data suggest that HLA-DRB1*11 and HLA-A*24 are likely to be predictive factors for immunological and clinical responses to vaccination with AE37, though prospective validation in larger cohorts is needed.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521656</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521655</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Eigl, BJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">North, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Winquist, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Finch, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wood, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sridhar, SS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Powers, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Good, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sharma, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Squire, JA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bazov, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Jamaspishvili, T.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cox, ME.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bradbury, PA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Eisenhauer, EA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chi, KN.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">A phase II study of the HDAC inhibitor SB939 in patients with castration resistant prostate cancer: NCIC clinical trials group study IND195.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Investigational new drugs</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Investigational new drugs</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2016</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: SB939 is a potent oral inhibitor of class 1, 2, and 4 histone deacetylases (HDACs). These three HDAC classes are highly expressed in castration resistant prostate cancer (CRPC) and associated with poor clinical outcomes. We designed a phase II study of SB939 in men with metastatic CRPC.

METHODS: Patients received SB939 60 mg on alternate days three times per week for 3 weeks on a 4-week cycle. Primary endpoints were PSA response rate (RR) and progression-free survival (PFS). Secondary endpoints included objective response rate and duration; overall survival; circulating tumor cell (CTC) enumeration and safety. Exploratory correlative studies of the TMPRSS2-ERG fusion and PTEN biomarkers were also performed.

RESULTS: Thirty-two patients were enrolled of whom 88 % had received no prior chemotherapy. The median number of SB939 cycles administered was three (range 1-8). Adverse events were generally grade 1-2, with five pts experiencing one or more grade three event. One patient died due to myocardial infarction. A confirmed PSA response was noted in two pts (6 %), lasting 3.0 and 21.6 months. In patients with measurable disease there were no objective responses. Six patients had stable disease lasting 1.7 to 8.0 months. CTC response (from ≥5 at baseline to &lt;5 at 6 or 12 weeks) occurred in 9/14 evaluable patients (64 %).

CONCLUSION: Although SB939 was tolerable at the dose/schedule given, and showed declines in CTC in the majority of evaluable patients, it did not show sufficient activity based on PSA RR to warrant further study as a single agent in unselected patients with CRPC.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521655</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521654</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kang, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lee, KM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Park, SK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Berndt, SI.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Reding, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chatterjee, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Welch, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chanock, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Huang, WY.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hayes, RB.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lack of association of transforming growth factor-beta1 polymorphisms and haplotypes with prostate cancer risk in the prostate, lung, colorectal, and ovarian trial.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer epidemiology, biomarkers &amp; prevention : a publication of the American Association for Cancer Research, cosponsored by the American Society of Preventive Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer epidemiology, biomarkers &amp; prevention : a publication of the American Association for Cancer Research, cosponsored by the American Society of Preventive Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2007</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal"/></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521654</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521653</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Palma, DA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Olson, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Harrow, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Correa, RJM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Schneiders, F.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Haasbeek, CJA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rodrigues, GB.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lock, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yaremko, BP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bauman, GS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ahmad, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Schellenberg, D.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Liu, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gaede, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Laba, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mulroy, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Senthi, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Louie, AV.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Swaminath, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chalmers, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Warner, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Slotman, BJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">de Gruijl, TD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Allan, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Senan, S.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Stereotactic ablative radiotherapy for the comprehensive treatment of 4-10 oligometastatic tumors (SABR-COMET-10): study protocol for a randomized phase III trial.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BMC cancer</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BMC cancer</style></full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Cancer</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Oligometastases</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Quality of life</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Stereotactic radiotherapy</style></keyword><keyword><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Survival</style></keyword></keywords><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2019</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: Stereotactic ablative radiotherapy (SABR) has emerged as a new treatment option for patients with oligometastatic disease. SABR delivers precise, high-dose, hypofractionated radiotherapy, and achieves excellent rates of local control for primary tumors or metastases. A recent randomized phase II trial evaluated SABR in a group of patients with a small burden of oligometastatic disease (mostly with 1-3 metastatic lesions), and found that SABR was associated with benefits in progression-free survival and overall survival. The goal of this phase III trial is to assess the impact of SABR in patients with 4-10 metastatic cancer lesions.

METHODS: One hundred and fifty-nine patients will be randomized in a 1:2 ratio between the control arm (consisting of standard of care palliative-intent treatments), and the SABR arm (consisting of standard of care treatment + SABR to all sites of known disease). Randomization will be stratified by two factors: histology (Group 1: prostate, breast, or renal; Group 2: all others), and type of pre-specified systemic therapy (Group 1: immunotherapy/targeted; Group 2: cytotoxic; Group 3: observation). SABR is to be completed within 2 weeks, allowing for rapid initiation of systemic therapy. Recommended SABR doses are 20 Gy in 1 fraction, 30 Gy in 3 fractions, or 35 Gy in 5 fractions, chosen to minimize risks of toxicity. The primary endpoint is overall survival, and secondary endpoints include progression-free survival, time to development of new metastatic lesions, quality of life, and toxicity. Translational endpoints include assessment of circulating tumor cells, cell-free DNA, and tumor tissue as prognostic and predictive markers, including assessment of immunological predictors of response and long-term survival.

DISCUSSION: This study will provide an assessment of the impact of SABR on clinical outcomes and quality of life, to determine if long-term survival can be achieved for selected patients with 4-10 oligometastatic lesions.

TRIAL REGISTRATION: Clinicaltrials.gov identifier: NCT03721341 . Date of registration: October 26, 2018.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521653</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521652</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Azad, NS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gray, RJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Overman, MJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Schoenfeld, JD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mitchell, EP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Zwiebel, JA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sharon, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Streicher, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Li, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">McShane, LM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Rubinstein, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Patton, DR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Williams, PM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Coffey, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hamilton, SR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Bahary, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Suga, JM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hatoum, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Abrams, JS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Conley, BA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Arteaga, CL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Harris, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">O'Dwyer, PJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chen, AP.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Flaherty, KT.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Nivolumab Is Effective in Mismatch Repair-Deficient Noncolorectal Cancers: Results From Arm Z1D-A Subprotocol of the NCI-MATCH (EAY131) Study.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Journal of clinical oncology : official journal of the American Society of Clinical Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2020</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">PURPOSE: The National Cancer Institute Molecular Analysis for Therapy Choice (NCI-MATCH) trial, the largest national precision oncology study to date (&gt; 1,100 sites) of patients with relapsed or refractory malignancies, assigned patients to targeted therapy in parallel phase II studies based on tumor molecular alterations. The anti-programmed death receptor 1 inhibitor nivolumab previously showed activity in mismatch repair (MMR)-deficient colon cancer. We hypothesized that nivolumab would have activity in patients with MMR-deficient, noncolorectal tumors.

PATIENTS AND METHODS: Eligible patients with relapsed or refractory tumors, good end-organ function, and Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of ≤ 1 underwent tumor biopsy for centralized screening of molecular alterations. MMR deficiency was defined by complete loss of nuclear expression of&lt;i&gt;MLH1&lt;/i&gt;or&lt;i&gt;MSH2&lt;/i&gt;MMR gene products by immunohistochemistry (IHC). Patients with MMR-deficient colorectal cancer were excluded. Nivolumab, 3 mg/kg every 2 weeks (28-day cycles) and 480 mg every 4 weeks after cycle 4, was administered intravenously. Disease reassessment was performed every 2 cycles. The primary end point was RECIST 1.1 objective response rate (ORR).

RESULTS: Two percent of 4,902 screened patients had an MMR-deficient cancer by IHC. Forty-two evaluable patients were enrolled, with a median age of 60 years and a median of 3 prior therapies. The most common histologies were endometrioid endometrial adenocarcinoma (n = 13), prostate adenocarcinoma (n = 5), and uterine carcinosarcoma (n = 4). ORR was 36% (15 of 42 patients). An additional 21% of patients had stable disease. The estimated 6-, 12-, and 18-month progression-free survival rates were 51.3% (90% CI, 38.2% to 64.5%), 46.2% (90% CI, 33.1% to 59.3%), and 31.4% (90% CI, 18.7% to 44.2%), respectively. Median overall survival was 17.3 months. Toxicity was predominantly low grade.

CONCLUSION: A variety of refractory cancers (2.0% of those screened) had MMR deficiency as defined in NCI-MATCH. Nivolumab has promising activity in MMR-deficient noncolorectal cancers of a wide variety of histopathologic types.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521652</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521651</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sandhu, SK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Schelman, WR.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wilding, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Moreno, V.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Baird, RD.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Miranda, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hylands, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Riisnaes, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Forster, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Omlin, A.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kreischer, N.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thway, K.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gevensleben, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sun, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Loughney, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chatterjee, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Toniatti, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carpenter, CL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Iannone, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kaye, SB.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">de Bono, JS.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wenham, RM.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase inhibitor niraparib (MK4827) in BRCA mutation carriers and patients with sporadic cancer: a phase 1 dose-escalation trial.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The Lancet. Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">The Lancet. Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2013</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: Poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) is implicated in DNA repair and transcription regulation. Niraparib (MK4827) is an oral potent, selective PARP-1 and PARP-2 inhibitor that induces synthetic lethality in preclinical tumour models with loss of BRCA and PTEN function. We investigated the safety, tolerability, maximum tolerated dose, pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profiles, and preliminary antitumour activity of niraparib.

METHODS: In a phase 1 dose-escalation study, we enrolled patients with advanced solid tumours at one site in the UK and two sites in the USA. Eligible patients were aged at least 18 years; had a life expectancy of at least 12 weeks; had an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of 2 or less; had assessable disease; were not suitable to receive any established treatments; had adequate organ function; and had discontinued any previous anticancer treatments at least 4 weeks previously. In part A, cohorts of three to six patients, enriched for BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers, received niraparib daily at ten escalating doses from 30 mg to 400 mg in a 21-day cycle to establish the maximum tolerated dose. Dose expansion at the maximum tolerated dose was pursued in 15 patients to confirm tolerability. In part B, we further investigated the maximum tolerated dose in patients with sporadic platinum-resistant high-grade serous ovarian cancer and sporadic prostate cancer. We obtained blood, circulating tumour cells, and optional paired tumour biopsies for pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic assessments. Toxic effects were assessed by common toxicity criteria and tumour responses ascribed by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST). Circulating tumour cells and archival tumour tissue in prostate patients were analysed for exploratory putative predictive biomarkers, such as loss of PTEN expression and ETS rearrangements. This trial is registered with ClinicalTrials.gov, NCT00749502.

FINDINGS: Between Sept 15, 2008, and Jan 14, 2011, we enrolled 100 patients: 60 in part A and 40 in part B. 300 mg/day was established as the maximum tolerated dose. Dose-limiting toxic effects reported in the first cycle were grade 3 fatigue (one patient given 30 mg/day), grade 3 pneumonitis (one given 60 mg/day), and grade 4 thrombocytopenia (two given 400 mg/day). Common treatment-related toxic effects were anaemia (48 patients [48%]), nausea (42 [42%]), fatigue (42 [42%]), thrombocytopenia (35 [35%]), anorexia (26 [26%]), neutropenia (24 [24%]), constipation (23 [23%]), and vomiting (20 [20%]), and were predominantly grade 1 or 2. Pharmacokinetics were dose proportional and the mean terminal elimination half-life was 36·4 h (range 32·8-46·0). Pharmacodynamic analyses confirmed PARP inhibition exceeded 50% at doses greater than 80 mg/day and antitumour activity was documented beyond doses of 60 mg/day. Eight (40% [95% CI 19-64]) of 20 BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation carriers with ovarian cancer had RECIST partial responses, as did two (50% [7-93]) of four mutation carriers with breast cancer. Antitumour activity was also reported in sporadic high-grade serous ovarian cancer, non-small-cell lung cancer, and prostate cancer. We recorded no correlation between loss of PTEN expression or ETS rearrangements and measures of antitumour activity in patients with prostate cancer.

INTERPRETATION: A recommended phase 2 dose of 300 mg/day niraparib is well tolerated. Niraparib should be further assessed in inherited and sporadic cancers with homologous recombination DNA repair defects and to target PARP-mediated transcription in cancer.

FUNDING: Merck Sharp and Dohme.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521651</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521650</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Kohli, M.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Ho, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hillman, DW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Van Etten, JL.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Henzler, C.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yang, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sperger, JM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Li, Y.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tseng, E.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Hon, T.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clark, T.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Tan, W.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Carlson, RE.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wang, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Sicotte, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Thai, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Jimenez, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Huang, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Vedell, PT.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Eckloff, BW.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Quevedo, JF.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Pitot, HC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Costello, BA.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Jen, J.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wieben, ED.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Silverstein, KAT.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Lang, JM.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Wang, L.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Dehm, SM.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Androgen Receptor Variant AR-V9 Is Coexpressed with AR-V7 in Prostate Cancer Metastases and Predicts Abiraterone Resistance.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2018</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">&lt;b&gt;Purpose:&lt;/b&gt;Androgen receptor (AR) variant AR-V7 is a ligand-independent transcription factor that promotes prostate cancer resistance to AR-targeted therapies. Accordingly, efforts are under way to develop strategies for monitoring and inhibiting AR-V7 in castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC). The purpose of this study was to understand whether other AR variants may be coexpressed with AR-V7 and promote resistance to AR-targeted therapies.&lt;b&gt;Experimental Design:&lt;/b&gt;We utilized complementary short- and long-read sequencing of intact AR mRNA isoforms to characterize AR expression in CRPC models. Coexpression of AR-V7 and AR-V9 mRNA in CRPC metastases and circulating tumor cells was assessed by RNA-seq and RT-PCR, respectively. Expression of AR-V9 protein in CRPC models was evaluated with polyclonal antisera. Multivariate analysis was performed to test whether AR variant mRNA expression in metastatic tissues was associated with a 12-week progression-free survival endpoint in a prospective clinical trial of 78 CRPC-stage patients initiating therapy with the androgen synthesis inhibitor, abiraterone acetate.&lt;b&gt;Results:&lt;/b&gt;AR-V9 was frequently coexpressed with AR-V7. Both AR variant species were found to share a common 3' terminal cryptic exon, which rendered AR-V9 susceptible to experimental manipulations that were previously thought to target AR-V7 uniquely. AR-V9 promoted ligand-independent growth of prostate cancer cells. High AR-V9 mRNA expression in CRPC metastases was predictive of primary resistance to abiraterone acetate (HR = 4.0; 95% confidence interval, 1.31-12.2;&lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt;= 0.02).&lt;b&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/b&gt;AR-V9 may be an important component of therapeutic resistance in CRPC.&lt;i&gt;Clin Cancer Res; 23(16); 4704-15. ©2017 AACR&lt;/i&gt;.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521650</custom4><custom5></custom5></record><record><database name="Articles_77566_20210715.enl">Articles_77566_20210715.enl</database><source-app version="17.7" name="EndNote">EndNote</source-app><rec-number>11521649</rec-number><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Chew, HK.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Somlo, G.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Mack, PC.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gitlitz, B.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Gandour-Edwards, R.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Christensen, S.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Linden, H.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Solis, LJ.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Yang, X.</style></author><author><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Davies, AM.</style></author></authors></contributors><titles><title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Phase I study of continuous and intermittent schedules of lapatinib in combination with vinorelbine in solid tumors.</style></title><secondary-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Annals of oncology : official journal of the European Society for Medical Oncology</style></secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">Annals of oncology : official journal of the European Society for Medical Oncology</style></full-title></periodical><dates><year><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">2012</style></year></dates><abstract><style size="100%" font="default" face="normal">BACKGROUND: Chemotherapy in combination with small-molecule epidermal growth factor receptor inhibitors has yielded inconsistent results. Based on preclinical models, we conducted a phase I trial of two schedules of lapatinib and vinorelbine.

PATIENT AND METHODS: Patients had advanced solid tumors and up to two prior chemotherapeutic regimens. Patients were enrolled on two dose-escalating schedules of lapatinib, continuous (arm A) or intermittent (arm B), with vinorelbine on days 1, 8, and 15 of a 28-day cycle. Tumors from a subset of patients were evaluated for gene mutations and expression of targets of interest.

RESULTS: Fifty-one patients were treated. The most common grade 3/4 toxic effects included leukopenia, neutropenia, and fatigue. Dose-limiting toxic effects were grade 3 infection, febrile neutropenia, and diarrhea (arm A) and bone pain and fatigue (arm B). The maximum tolerated dose was vinorelbine 20 mg/m(2) weekly and lapatinib 1500 mg daily (arm A) and vinorelbine 25 mg/m(2) weekly and lapatinib 1500 mg intermittently (arm B). One patient on each arm had a complete response; both had human epidermal growth factor receptor 2-positive breast cancer. In a subset of patients, lack of tumor PTEN expression correlated with a shorter time to progression.

CONCLUSION: In an unselected population, two schedules of lapatinib and vinorelbine were feasible and well tolerated.</style></abstract><urls/><custom4>11521649</custom4><custom5></custom5></record></records></xml>